- [Instructor] Welcome
back, in this video,
we're gonna talk about security groups.
If you're ready, let's begin.
All right, so what is a security group?
A security group acts
as a virtual firewall
that controls the traffic for
one or more EC2 instances.
When you launch an
instance you associate one
or more security groups
with that instance.
So it is not that we can only
associate one security group
per instance, we could associate
multiple security groups
per EC2 instance.
We add rules to each security group
that allow traffic to, or
from, its associated instances.
We can modify the rules of a
security group at any time,
and the new rules are
automatically applied
to all instances that are associated
with the security group.
In the next video, when
we'll be doing a hands-on
on security groups, we'll
see this live in action.
We will modify the security group
and we'll notice that
as soon as you modify,
the changes are applied immediately.
Every security group
can have different set
of rules for inbound,
and outbound traffic.
By default security groups
allow all outbound traffic.
When we create a security
group, it has no inbound rules,
therefore, no inbound traffic originating
from another host to your
EC2 instance is allowed,
until you add inbound rules
to the security group.
So, by default, everything
is allowed outbound,
nothing is allowed inbound.
We can specify separate rules for inbound,
and outbound traffic.
Very important - security group
rules are always permissive.
We can't write rules that deny access.
That means when we are
defining a security group,
we can only write rules
that allow traffic towards the instance,
or from the instance, but
we cannot write a rule
that blocks the traffic
or denies the traffic.
Security groups are stateful in nature,
which means if you send a
request from your instance,
the response traffic for
that request is allowed
to flow in regardless of
inbound security group rules.
Let me explain this to
you with an example.
So on the screen right now
I have an EC2 instance,
and I have a security group,
which is shown in red dotted lines.
The EC2 instance is trying to
reach a server on the internet
which is shown on the left hand side.
When the EC2 instance sends the traffic,
it first gets processed
by the security group.
Let's assume that this traffic is allowed
by the security group, so this
traffic reaches the server.
Now when the server responds back,
and when the response
hits the security group,
is it gonna be evaluated again?
The answer is no.
When the server responds back,
the traffic will be automatically allowed
to reach that EC2 instance.
It will not be processed against
the security rules again.
Since the response belongs
to an existing session,
it is allowed to flow in.
And this is known as stateful inspection.
Security groups are stateful in nature.
They allows responses to flow in,
regardless of the inbound
rule configuration.
Let's now talk about security group rules.
Every security group must have
a name, and a description,
and these can be up to
255 characters in length.
A security group name
cannot start with sg-.
There are limits on the
number of security groups
that you can create per
VPC, the number of rules
that you can add to each security group,
and the number of security groups
that you can associate
with a network interface.
When we configure a security group,
these are the items
that we need to define.
Number one, we must specify the protocol.
The most common protocols
are TCP, UDP, and ICMP.
Next, we need to specify the port range,
which can be a single
port, or a range of ports,
for TCP or UDP, or the custom protocol.
Next, we specify the
source or destination.
The source is for inbound rules,
and destination is for outbound rules.
If you must specify
individual IPV for addresses,
they must be configured
with the /32 prefix length.
For example, 4.2.2.2/32.
If you need to specify
individual IPv6 addresses,
they must use /128 prefix length.
And you have an example
on the screen as well.
As you can see it has a
prefix length of /128.
Interestingly, the source or destination
of a security group can also
be another security group.
This allows EC2 instances associated
with the specified security group
to access instances associated
with this security group.
If that sounds too confusing,
I have an example coming up for you.
Additionally, you may also
configure ICMP type and code.
This is applicable only if you
select the protocol as ICMP.
Now, I'm gonna show you an example
of how a security group can be referenced
within another security group.
On the screen right now,
I have an EC2 instance
which represents a web server.
And as you can see, the
EC2 instance is associated
with a security group which is shown
with the red dotted line.
Also, I have a database server,
which has its own security group.
The web server is connected
with the database server.
People on the internet need
to access the web server.
However, we do not want to
permit people on the internet
to be directly accessing
the database server.
That means users can
access the web server,
and the web server has a connection
with the database server.
How do we make this happen?
How do we make sure that people
on the internet can connect
to the web server, but then
they cannot directly connect
with the database server?
The only connection that is permitted
on the database server is that
which originates from the web server.
The security group associated
with the web server
is called as web-server-sg.
When I'm defining the security group
for my database server, this
is how I'm gonna configure it.
As you can see over here,
I've given it a name,
which is called as database sg.
I've given it a description.
Notice the inbound traffic.
I've selected MYSQL on TCP 3306,
which is the traffic for database servers.
The source is a custom IP address,
but then, look at the
source that I've specified.
In the source field I have given the name
of the security group that is associated
with the web server
which is web-server-sg.
And you can see that over here.
This means this security group,
which is associated with
the database server,
is only going to allow
inbound traffic on TCP 3306
that originates from
any instance associated
with web-server-sg.
This is interesting because I do not have
to specify the IP
address of my web server.
Any instance that is associated
with web-server-sg will
automatically be able
to access the database servers.
At the same time, it will
prevent any other connections.
Isn't this really fantastic?
We can actually reference security groups
within security groups.
And this applies to
outbound traffic as well.
Moving on, some more
rules for security groups.
If there is more than one
rule for a specific port,
the most permissive rule is applied.
For example, let's say you have a rule
that allows access to TCP port 22,
which is the SSH port number,
from a specific IP address
which is 203.0.113.1.
And you also have another
rule that allows access
to TCP port 22 from everywhere.
In this case, everyone would
have access to TCP port 22.
The bottom line is, the most
permissive rule is applied.
When multiple security
groups are associated
with an instance, the rules
from each security group
are effectively aggregated
to create one set of rules.
And this set of rules is used to determine
whether to allow access.
We also have something called
as the default security group.
Every AWS account has a
default security group per VPC.
If you don't specify a
security group when you launch
an EC2 instance, the instance
is automatically associated
with the default security group.
The default security
group is named as default,
and it has and ID assigned by AWS.
Please also note that we cannot delete
the default security group.
Well, that's it for this video.
I hope you enjoyed this one.
In the next video we're gonna do hands on,
and we're gonna implement
all of these concepts.
I'm excited to see you there
and I'd like to thank you for watching.
Thank you.