- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video, we're gonna do some
hands-on exercises on security groups.
We'll implement all the concepts
that we understood in the last video.
If you're ready, let's begin.
All right, so I'm here at the AWS console
and, as you can see right now,
I'm in the tab called Instances
and I have one running EC2 instance.
If I wanted to see what
security group has been assigned
to this EC2 instance, I can
just drop down over here.
In the panel over here, I can see that
I have something called Security Groups
and this is the name of the security group
which is currently assigned.
It's called as SSH and ICMP allowed.
If I wanted to view the inbound rules
I could click on view inbound
rules and we can see that
a couple of protocols is allowed inbound.
The first one is tcp,
port 22, which is SSH.
It is allowed from all
source IP addresses.
And then ICMP is also allowed
from all the source IP addresses.
How about creating some
new security groups?
To create additional
security groups, we could
go down to this tab over
here called Security Groups.
Right now, I have about
four security groups
out of which one is default
and three are user-created.
If I wanted to create
a new security group,
I can click on Create Security Group
and we need to first
start by giving it a name.
I'm gonna call this one as HTTP allowed.
I'm also gonna give it a description.
Okay, and then we can also select the VPC.
In this case, I only have the default VPC.
Over here, we have two tabs,
one for Inbound and one for Outbound.
As you can see, the Inbound
tab has no rules right now.
But if I go to Outbound, by default,
all outbound traffic is allowed.
If I wanted to change that, I
can go to the right-hand side,
and I can click on this
cross to remove that rule.
If I wanted to add a new rule,
I can click on Add Rule over here.
Right now, I'm gonna
leave it the way it is
and go back to Inbound
and I'm gonna add a rule
to allow Inbound HTTP traffic.
So I click on Add Rule over here.
The first thing is the type of traffic.
There are some pre-defined traffic types.
You can choose from one of them.
For example, you have SSH, SMTP, DNS,
HTTP, LDAP, IMAP, et cetera.
If you'd like to define
your custom traffic type,
you could use one of
the options over here.
For ICMP, you could use one
of these options over here.
If you wanna allow everything inbound,
you can go for All traffic.
Right now, I'm trying to allow HTTP.
So I'm gonna select this
one over here, HTTP.
By default, it selects the protocol as TCP
and the port number as 80.
Over here, I can define
the source of that traffic.
If I give My IP, it takes
my public IP address.
If I give Custom, I can define
my custom IP address range over here.
Of, if I give Anywhere,
it takes all IP addresses.
We can also give a description over here.
If you wanted to add a new
rule, you can say Add Rule
and you can define that traffic over here.
Right now, I'm gonna remove that
and have just one rule over here.
Before I click on Create,
I also wanna show you
something very interesting.
If I select Custom over
here, notice what it says.
Enter the CIDR, the IP or the name
of another Security Group.
Remember the example from the last video
where we understood that
we only wanted to allow
inbound traffic to the database
server from the web server.
All other traffic should not be allowed.
So, if you want to allow
traffic from instances
that are associated with
a specific security group,
you can call that
security group over here.
For example, if I wanted
to allow inbound traffic
from all EC2 instances associated with
this security group called web-server,
I could specify that as the source.
So right now, I'm gonna say Anywhere
to allow HTTP traffic from anywhere.
And I'm gonna click on Create over here.
So my security group has been created
and it's over here, HTTP allowed.
If you wanted to modify an
existing security group,
you can go to Actions and you can say,
Edit inbound rules or Edit outbound rules.
Notice that you can also
add tags to security groups.
If you wanted to view the
inbound and outbound rules,
you can go to this tab
over here called Inbound.
We can see that we have HTTP traffic.
Notice that it shows you two rows.
This one is for any IPv4 traffic
and this one is for any IPv6 traffic.
And if you wanted to
view the outbound rules,
you could go over here to
the tab called Outbound
and we can see that everything
is allowed outbound.
Now let's try to associate this
with an existing EC2 instance.
So I go back to Instances over here.
I have my running instance,
which is associated
with one security group,
which is SSH and ICMP allowed.
To associate another security group,
I would go to Actions, Networking,
Change Security Groups.
We can see that we have
one allowed right now,
or one enabled right now,
and I'm also going to enable this one,
which is HTTP allowed.
And I'm gonna click on
Assign Security Groups.
So now, we have a couple
of security groups
associated with that EC2 instance.
If I click on view inbound rules,
we can now see that we
have port 22 tcp and icmp
from the first security group,
you can see that over here.
And we have port 80, tcp, from
the second security group,
which is called as HTTP allowed.
So, in the last video, we
said that we can attach
multiple security groups
to the same EC2 instance.
In this case, AWS would create
a larger security group,
which is a combination of everything,
and that would be used to decide
what traffic is allowed
inbound or outbound.
Remember we also understood that,
changes to security groups are applied
automatically and immediately.
Let's take a look at that.
So right now, we have
ICMP allowed inbound.
Let's try to ping this EC2 instance.
So I'm gonna copy that IP address
and I'm gonna open up a terminal.
And I'm gonna try and
ping that IP address.
And, as we can see that
we're getting replies
from that EC2 instance.
Now let's remove ICMP
from that security group.
So I'm gonna come back to the AWS console,
go to Security Groups.
This is the security group
which has been applied
to that EC2 instance,
SSH and ICMP allowed.
We can see that in the
Inbound tab, ICMP is allowed.
Now, I'm gonna go to
Actions, Edit inbound rules,
and I'm gonna remove both of these items.
ICMP from IPv4 and ICMP from all IPv6.
I'm gonna remove that and click on Save.
So, at this point, only SSH
traffic is being allowed.
If we go back to Instances,
click on the EC2 instance,
we can see that, when we
click on view inbound rules,
there's no ICMP over here.
When I go back to my terminal,
you can see that the
ping is still working.
How is that possible?
Well, the reason is, even though
the rule is applied immediately,
the existing conditions are not affected.
And this is a very critical learning.
Even if you make a change
to your security group,
existing connections
stay the way they are.
But notice what happens if I do
a control + C to terminate that.
I hit the up arrow, which
is ping, and the IP address,
and then when I do an
Enter, you'll notice that
now I'm getting timed out.
New connections take effect.
Existing connections
stay the way they are.
Well, that's it for this video.
I hope you enjoyed this one.
I'd like to thank you for watching
and I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.