- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video, we'll
continue our discussion
on security groups, and we'll understand
how we can use security groups
as source or destination
for another security group.
So in the last couple of videos,
we looked at the concepts
of security groups,
and we also understood
how we can configure
inbound and outbound
rules for security groups.
In this video, I'm gonna show you exactly
how you can use security groups
as a source or destination
for another security group.
If you're ready, let's begin.
Alright, so I'm here at the AWS console,
and you can see right now,
I have no running instances.
The first thing that we'll do is
we'll spin up a new web server.
This one is a lab exercise,
so I hope you're signed
into your AWS account,
and let's do it together.
We'll go to launch instance.
This lab can be done on a Windows machine
and on a Linux machine as well,
but we can do it very quickly
if we choose to do it
on a Linux based system.
So let's do that.
We can select the first one over here
which is Amazon Linux AMI.
We'll select the size as t2 micro,
because that is free tier eligible.
Click on next.
Now you can choose any
availability zone of your choice,
just make sure that you
have auto-assign public IP
set to enable, or the subnet setting,
if that is set to enable,
because we need a public IP
to access the web server.
Down over here, in advanced details,
I'm gonna write a small startup script.
I have that ready, so I'm just
gonna paste that over here.
I'll explain it to you.
There are four commands.
The first command instructs
the operating system
to run all the remaining commands
with the required privileges.
This one over here, yum
install httpd minus y
installs Apache on the Linux server.
This one over here starts
the Apache service.
And finally, I'm gonna
write a small HTML code
inside a file called as index.html.
The index.html file is in the root folder,
which is /var/www/html.
It's a simple code, it
says hi, I'm a web server,
within the h1 tag.
In the description of this video,
I will leave this code snip-it
so you can just copy and paste it.
By the way, we've not discussed
about user data before.
User data is a very handy way
to pass some startup scripts
to EC2 instances.
Whatever we input in user data
is executed at startup when
the EC2 instance boots up.
Right, so now I'm gonna
say next add storage.
Eight gigs of storage is absolutely fine.
Next we'll add some tags.
Let's call this as WebServer.
Next we need to create a security group.
Now the security group needs to allow
two kinds of protocols, SSH and HTTP.
SSH will allow us to log
in to the EC2 instance
if we need to troubleshoot,
and HTTP will be used
to access the web page.
So I'll create a new one.
I'll call it as SSH and HTTP allowed,
and I'll copy that in the description.
We already have SSH, we'll also add HTTP,
from all IP addresses,
review and launch, launch,
and I'll make sure that I
have access to the key pair,
and launch instances.
Now the instance is being launched.
We can go to view instances.
Refresh that.
After about 30 seconds,
the instance is now in a running state,
and I'm gonna copy that public IP address,
and I'm gonna try that
in a new browser window.
Hit enter, and there you go.
It says Hi, I'm a web server.
Fantastic.
Next, we're gonna create
a new load balancer.
So we'll go to this section over here,
which is called as load balancers.
We're doing this just to
test this lab exercise.
Later on in this course,
we have a dedicated
discussion on load balancers
where we'll deep dive
into all the concepts
of load balancers.
Right now, I'm just
trying to show you a lab
on security groups, so we'll
not be discussing all concepts
related to load balancers.
We're just gonna launch
it and test it, okay?
So let's do create load balancer.
We have three types of load balancers,
application, network, and classic.
Let's go with classic.
Click on create.
We'll give it a name, I'm gonna call it as
my elastic load balancer.
The load balancing protocol
is HTTP on port 80,
and the instance also
responds on HTTP on port 80,
which is fine.
Next, assign a security group.
Now, we could assign this one over here
because it already has HTTP allowed,
but I'm gonna create a new one,
and you'll know shortly why.
So I'm gonna call this
one as HTTP for ELB,
or maybe HTTP for myELB.
I'll copy and paste
that in the description,
and the type of traffic will be HTTP.
Next, we're not gonna
configure any security settings
right now, we'll go on
to the health check.
The health check is a way by
which the load balancer knows
that the instance that is
sitting behind the load balancer
is healthy and functioning.
And for that, the load
balancer tries to access a file
on that instance.
Or we can say that the
load balancer tries to ping
the instance behind it.
In this case, it is gonna use
the HTTP protocol for ping,
on port 80, and it will
try to ping this file,
which is index.html,
and we know that we already have this file
because we actually created a web page
by writing a little piece
of code inside that file.
These are some values which are used
to configure the load balancer.
Right now, we're not gonna get into that.
We have another dedicated
discussion for that.
We'll move on.
We'll say add EC2 instances.
Right now, we only have
one running instance,
so I'm gonna select that, click on next.
You could add tags if you wanted to.
Right now, I'm not gonna do that.
Review and create, and click on create.
So now, the load balancer
is being created.
Click on close.
We can see that load balancer over here,
and if we go to instances,
we have that one EC2
instance that we selected.
It's called as WebServer,
and right now it says out of service.
Now we need to wait for some time
until it becomes in service,
and it can take up to one or two minutes,
depending on the values that we configured
while creating the load balancer.
So let's just pause
this video for a second,
and I'll come back when
this is in service.
Alright, so after waiting
for about a minute or so,
the status is now in service,
which means the load balancer
is forwarding traffic
to the instance that is sitting behind it.
How do we test this?
So we can go to description over here.
From here, we can grab the DNS
name of that load balancer,
we can copy that, we can
go to a new browser window,
we can type that and hit enter,
and it should show you the same web page,
because the load balancer
takes that traffic
and forwards that to the web server.
This is fantastic,
everything is working well.
But there's a small problem.
The problem is customers on the internet
can access this web page using
the load balancer DNS name.
However, they can also
directly access the web page
with the IP address of that server.
If this is possible,
it defeats the purpose of
having a load balancer.
We have a load balancer
so that customers can
hit the load balancer
and the traffic gets load balanced
between multiple instances.
In this case, yes we
have only one instance,
but assuming that we
had multiple instances,
the traffic would be load balanced.
Ideally, we do not want customers
to access the server directly,
so we need to configure this in a way
that the website is accessible
only if you hit the load balancer,
not if you hit the IP
address of that server.
How do we do that?
Simple, we just need to
modify the security group
that is associated with this web server.
So back over here to the EC2 console,
we'll go back to instances over here,
and first of all, we wanna verify
what is the security
group that is associated
with this web server?
So this is my web server.
If I go down over here, I can see that
the security group is called
as SSH and HTTP allowed.
So we'll go to security groups over here,
we'll click on SSH and HTTP allowed,
and we'll edit the inbound rule.
Over here, we can see that
there are two entries for HTTP,
one that allows traffic
from all IPv4 addresses,
and one that allows traffic
from all IPv6 addresses.
To keep things simple,
let's remove the IPv6 rule,
so now we're only allowing
traffic from all IPv4 addresses.
And that's the problem,
because it is accepting
traffic from all sources.
We want to modify this.
We want to make sure that
the traffic is allowed
only if it is associated
with the load balancer,
and the way to do that is to remove this
and call the security group
that is associated with
that load balancer.
So I'll remove that, and
I'll start by typing in sg,
because security groups have an identifier
which starts with sg, and
we can see that over here,
we have a security group
called HTTP for myELB,
and this is the one that we
created for the load balancer.
So we select that.
Now what happens?
The server will allow HTTP
traffic for only those instances
or resources that are associated
with this security group.
Let's click on save, alright.
Now, we'll verify this.
We go back over here,
and if we do a refresh,
it's working fine, but what about this?
Let's do a refresh over here,
and you can see that it's timing out.
In fact, if I copy that
and try that in a new browser
window, it will not work.
The security group will
now accept traffic only if
it is associated with an
instance or a resource
that uses the security
group that we specified.
Similarly, you could
also do outbound rules,
you can go to actions,
and edit inbound rules,
sorry, edit outbound rules,
and if you had a specific use case,
you could also put a
security group over here.
Alright, so that's about this lecture.
Just make sure that you clean
up your lab environment,
delete your load balancers,
they're very expensive,
and also terminate your EC2 instance.
I'd like to thank you for watching,
and I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.