- [Narrator] Welcome back.
In this video, we're
going to do some hands on
exercises on AMIs.
In one of the earlier
lectures, we spoke about AMIs,
or Amazon Machine Images,
and we spoke about this
in the lecture where we
understood how to launch
an EC2 instance.
We saw that selecting
an AMI is the first step
when you are creating an EC2 instance,
and we also understood
that an AMI is a template
that contains all the required information
to launch an EC2 instance.
In this video, we're going to understand
how to create our own custom AMIs.
If you are ready, let's begin.
All right, so right now
I'm at the AWS console
and as you can see right
now I have a running
Windows EC2 instance.
This one is a Windows 2008 instance
and I have already connected
to this EC2 instance.
So, here you can see that
I'm already connected
to that EC2 instance and
after connecting I have
installed something called as XAMPP.
XAMPP is an Apache distribution
and it's an open source tool.
So, you can see that I
already have it installed.
The reason I'm doing this is to show you
what happens when you create an AMI
out of this EC2 instance.
Let's go back to the AWS console.
Back over here, when I
select the EC2 instance
you can see that I have
two volumes attached
to that EC2 instance,
and I can confirm this
by going to volumes over here.
So you can see that we
have a couple of volumes.
One is 30 gigs, and
one is one gig in size.
Before we start the
process of creating the AMI
let's first launch a
continuous ping on the public
IP address of that EC2 instance.
So, I'll go back to instances over here,
copy that public IP
address, open up a terminal,
and I'm gonna do a ping, and
the IP address, hit enter.
So right now we have connectivity
to that EC2 instance.
If I wanted to create an
AMI I would select that
EC2 instance, go to actions,
image, create image.
We can give it a name.
I'm gonna call it as
Windows 2008 with XAMPP.
Notice that both the
volumes are going to be
part of the AMI, and we
also have a check box
over here that says no reboot.
Right now I'm gonna leave that unchecked
and see what happens.
Now, I'm gonna click on
create image over here
and we can see that the
create image request
has been received and the
process has been started.
I'm gonna close that and
go back to the terminal
to see what happens.
Back over here, the ping is still working.
I'm gonna give it about 30 seconds or so.
In fact, you can see that it
has already started timing out,
which means the EC2
instance has been rebooted
and this is something
very critical to know.
EC2 instances will be rebooted
if you try to create an AMI.
Right, if you don't want this to happen,
what you could do is you
could use the option called
no reboot, however, if
there is any data which is
sitting in the cache that
would not be a part of the AMI.
To make sure that all the
data is included in the AMI
ideally you want that EC2
instance to be rebooted.
Back over here, now I'm
gonna wait for some time
for that EC2 instance to come back online.
Meanwhile, we can go to
AMIs and we can see that
the AMI is being provisioned.
I'm gonna pause the video
here for a couple of minutes
until this moves to the available state.
All right, so after waiting
for about three minutes
the AMI is now completed.
The process has been completed,
and it is now available, which means
we can now use the AMI to
create new EC2 instances.
Let's do that now.
I'm gonna go to actions,
and I'm gonna say launch.
So now we are in the EC2
instance launch wizard.
I'm gonna say configure instance details.
I'm not gonna change anything over here,
leave everything at the default.
Notice that all the volumes from the AMI
or the original EC2 instance
are found over here.
We have the 30 gigs
volume, and we also have
the one gig volume.
If we did not want to
use this one over here,
the additional volume, we can remove that,
click on next, and I'm
gonna name it as WinServer2.
Configure security
group, and I'm gonna use
an existing security group
that allows RDP traffic,
preview and launch and launch,
and I'm gonna acknowledge
that I have access to that key pair.
Launch instances.
Now, the instance is being launched.
We can click on view instances,
and we see that WinServer2
is now being launched.
Now, this can take about
two to three minutes.
So meanwhile, I'm gonna
go back to AMIs over here.
We have that AMI, and
I'm also gonna show you
snapshots over here.
So we can see that we
have snapshots of both
the volumes of the original EC2 instance,
the 30 gig volume, and the
one gig volume as well.
Whenever you create a new AMI the new AMI
is automatically registered,
which means it becomes
available to create new EC2 instances.
If however you do not
want to allow the creation
of new instances from that
AMI you can de-register that
by going to actions, de-register.
If you want to modify the
permissions of that AMI
you can go to modify image permissions.
Right now the AMI's owned by
you and not shared with anyone.
If you would like to
share it with specific
AWS accounts you can use
this option called private,
and you can use the AWS
account number of the person
or the organization with
which you'd like to share.
If you want to make the AMI a public AMI
where you allow everybody to use that
you can use this option called public.
I'm gonna cancel out from here,
and back over here in the AMI
section right now you have
a filter applied called owned by me.
So it only shows you AMIs
that you have created.
If you want to see private
AMIs that have been shared
with you, you can change
that private images.
So you can see all the
private images over here,
and if you want to see the
public AMIs that are available
you can do public images.
So you can see there's 23,000
AMIs available to choose from.
I'm gonna reset it back to owned by me.
How about copying this
AMI to a different region?
Let's say I want to
launch a new EC2 instance
in a different region.
So you could go to actions and you can say
copy AMI and you can copy it
over to a different region.
When you're copying
them you can also choose
to encrypt your EBS snapshots.
I'm gonna cancel out from here.
Go back to instances, and now we have
the running EC2 instance.
Let's try to connect to that.
So I'm gonna select this one over here
and click on connect, and
I'm gonna say get password.
This is something that
I wanted you to see.
It says the password is not available.
This instance was
launched from a custom AMI
or the default password has changed.
So, AWS has no idea what
the password for this
EC2 instance is, because
the AMI was created
from this EC2 instance
and it could be possible
you have a custom password on that.
This is very, very important.
You must be aware of the password
required to connect to that EC2 instance.
Right now I have an
easier way to find out.
I can use connect on my first EC2 instance
and grab the password from there.
Decrypt the password.
This is my original password.
If I had changed this
from the control panel
of the Windows operating
system I would have
to use the new password.
So I'm gonna copy that,
and I'm gonna open up
a remote desktop client.
All right, and I'm gonna
start a new connection.
First of all, I'm gonna
copy that password.
Go back to the AWS console,
and copy the public IP address.
Back over here, I'm
gonna put that IP address
and the user name would be administrator.
I'm gonna close that to
save that connection.
Now, before I connect I'm
gonna terminate my session
with this EC2 instance.
All right, I've closed
that in the background.
Now I'm gonna establish a session with
the new EC2 instance called as WinServer2.
All right, I'm gonna accept that.
Okay, so now I have connected
to that EC2 instance
and I want you to notice something now.
If I go to start you'll notice that
XAMPP is pre-installed,
because the original
EC2 instance had XAMPP on
it, the AMI had XAMPP on it,
and the EC2 instance
created out of that AMI
also has XAMPP on it, which means
I can now use the AMI as a golden image
to create new EC2 instances.
Isn't this fantastic?
It makes things so much easier.
And finally, before I end this video
I'm gonna show you how to delete an AMI.
I'm back at the AWS console.
I'll go to AMIs.
There are two steps that
need to be performed
to delete the AMI.
The first thing is you go to actions
and you de-register that.
Continue.
So now, it has been de-registered,
which means the AMI cannot be used
to launch new EC2
instances, and to complete
the deletion process you would
go to snapshots over here
and you would delete all
snapshots off that AMI.
Now that the snapshots are deleted,
if you go back to AMIs you will still find
your AMI over there.
Now, this is something
that takes a little while.
It can take a few minutes for
the AMI to get removed from here.
All right, so that's it for this video.
I hope you enjoyed it.
If you have any questions,
please let me know.
I'd like to thank you for watching,
and I'll catch you in the
next video, thank you.