- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video, we're gonna discuss about
something known as EC2 Instance Store.
I'm sure you remember EBS volumes.
EBS volumes are block devices
that provide persistent storage.
Even if your EC2 Instance reboots,
you still have access to that data.
And EBS volumes can be
used as the root device
for the EC2 Instances.
We have another class of volumes
or we have another type of storage
which is not persistent in nature
but is temporary in nature.
And that is what is Instance Store.
Let's take a look at it.
Alright, so what is an Instance Store?
Some Amazon EC2 instance types
come with a form of directly attached,
block-device storage, which
is known as Instance Store.
The Instance Store is ideal
for temporary storage,
such as buffers and caches,
because the data stored
in Instance Store
volumes is not persistent
through instance stops,
terminations, or hardware failures.
An Instance Store consists of one
or more Instance Store volumes,
which are exposed as block devices.
The size of an Instance Store,
as well as the number of devices available
varies by instance type.
I have a diagram on the screen,
which tries to explain
how Instance Store volumes
are exposed as block devices.
A collection of these volumes together
is what is known as Instance Store.
And each of these volumes
are individually exposed
to the EC2 instance.
And we'll take a look at
that in just about a minute.
Back over here, let's talk about
the Instance Store Lifetime.
You can specify Instance Store volumes
for an instance only when you launch it.
And we'll look at this
in just about a minute.
We can detach an Instance Store volume
from one instance and attach
it to a different instance.
This one is a significant difference
compared to EBS volumes.
We could do this easily with EBS volumes.
Just detach the volume
from an EC2 instance
and attach that to another EC2 instance.
However, with Instance Store
volumes, that's not possible.
The data in an Instance Store persists
only during the lifetime
of its associated instance.
This is interesting.
If an instance reboots,
either intentionally or unintentionally,
data in the Instance Store still persists.
So that means, if your EC2
instance has been rebooted,
you still have access to that data.
However, data in the
Instance Store is lost
under the following circumstances.
Number one, the underlying
disk drive fails.
Number two, the instance stops.
And number three, the instance terminates.
Moving on.
When you stop or terminate an instance,
every block of storage in
the Instance Store is reset.
Therefore, your data cannot be accessed
through the Instance
Store of another instance.
Essentially, after you
terminate your EC2 instance,
if your Instance Store is allocated
to another customer, they
can't access your data,
because everything has been reset
before it is allocated
to the other customer.
If you create an AMI from an instance,
the data on its Instance
Store volumes isn't preserved
and isn't present on the
Instance Store volumes
of the instance that you
launch from the new AMI.
This is another significant difference
compared to EBS volumes.
With EBS volumes, whatever data is there,
it is transferred to the AMI
and when you create an EC2
instance out of that AMI,
the new instance also has that data,
but with Instance Store,
that's not the case.
Therefore, do not rely on Instance Store
for valuable, long-term data.
Instead, use more duruable data storage
such as Amazon S3, Amazon
EBS, or Amazon EFS,
which is Elastic File Storage.
So I'm back over here to this document.
I'm just gonna scroll down over here
and here, we have a nice eautiful table
that tells you every instance type
and what is the number
of Instance Store volumes
that you can attach.
For example, if you look at c1_medium,
you can attach one Instance
Store volume of size 350 gigs.
Or look at this guy, c1-xlarge,
you can attach four, each
having a size of 420 GB.
The largest is over here, d2_8xlarge.
It allows you to attach
24 Instance Store volumes,
each of size 2,000 gigs,
which is a massive amount of storage.
Now let's understand how
to launch an EC2 instance
with an Instance Store volume.
So I'm gonna take you
to the AWS EC2 console
and I'm gonna go to instances
and I'm gonna click on launch instance.
One way to launch an ES2 Instance Store
is to go to Community AMIs.
And down over here, we have a filter
where you can say, show me only those AMIs
whose root device happens
to be Instance Store.
So you can see that over here,
I have about 2,151 AMIs,
each of them having the root device
as Instance Store, temporary storage.
The other way of doing it
is you go to Quick Start
and you have all these
AMIs, about 35 of them,
each of them having
the root device as EBS.
You select any one of them.
Okay?
And now, here you have
all the instance sizes
and you have a column over here
that tells you how much Instance Store
can be added to each of
these instance types.
For example if you see only EBS, EBS only,
you cannot add an Instance Store volume,
but if you see something like this,
like this, which is x1.16xlarge,
you can attach one Instance
Store volume of size 1920 gigs.
Moving on, you can see
over here, d2.8 xlarge.
It comes with 36 virtual
CPUs and it allows you
to attach 24 Instance Store
volumes. each of size 2048 gigs.
If you do not see this
column on your screen,
you can go to the top over here,
you can say Show Hide Columns
and you can just enable
this column over here.
Let met show you an example.
I'm gonna pick, let's
say this one over here,
i2.4xlarge, which gives me
four Instance Store volumes,
each of size 800 gigs.
I select that and I click on Next.
You can change your preferences over here.
I'm gonna select Next and notice that
I have the four Instance Store volumes.
If I do not want any one of them,
I an just remove that from here.
I also want you to notice,
the size is not in our control.
If it's an EBS volum,
we can decide the size,
but if it's Instance Store volume,
we do not have the option
to change the size.
The size is predetermined.
In this case, it is 800 gigs.
Now what I have done is,
before I started recording,
I already launched an EC2 instance
with an Instance Store
volume, which is i2.xlarge.
It has one Instance Store
and we can check that out
by logging into the EC2 instance.
After logging in, I'm gonna do sudo su
just to elevate my privileges
and I'm gonna try LSBLK to
view all the attached devices.
So this on is my root volume,
which is 8 8 gigs in size,
and this one here is the
Instance Store volume,
which is about 800 gigs in size.
We also notice that the root volume
has been mounted, of course,
but this one has not been mounted
so before we can start using
that, we need to mount tha
and if you've seen one
of the only lectures
on how to attach EBS
volumes to Linux devices,
you should be aware of how to mount
a volume onto a mount point.
Right.
So what's the bottom line?
The bottom line is EBS volumes
give you persistent storage,
while Instance Store volumes
give you temporary storage.
This is useful, especially
if your application
requires only temporary storage,
such as having a buffer or having a cache.
Well, that's about Instance Store volumes.
I'd like to thank you for watching
and I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.