- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video, we're
gonna focus our attention
on a specific EC2 instance type,
which is known as T2 instances.
There's something very special
about these EC2 instances
and that's exactly what
we're gonna understand
in this video.
If you are ready, let's begin.
Alright so what's special
about T2 instances?
Well, T2 instances are
designed to provide a baseline
level of CPU performance
with the ability to burst
to a higher level when
required by your workload.
T2 instances are the only
type of EC2 instances
which are known as
burstable EC2 instances.
Whereas all the other EC2
instance types are known as
fixed performance EC2 instances.
That is, all those EC2 instances
like M3, M4, I2, et cetera,
they give you a fixed
level of performance.
However, T2 instances give
you a baseline of performance,
and they also allow you to burst above,
when required by your workload.
Hence they're called as
burstable EC2 instances.
T2 instances are well
suited for a wide range
of general purpose applications, like,
microservices, low-latency
interactive applications,
small and medium databases,
virtual desktops, dev,
build and stage environments,
code repositories
and product prototypes.
As you can see,
they are well suited for a
lot of different applications.
Now I'm gonna introduce a
concept called as CPU credits.
Traditional Amazon EC2 instance types
provide fixed performance,
while T2 instances provide a
baseline of CPU performance
with the ability to burst
above that baseline level.
The baseline performance
and the ability to burst
is governed by something
called as CPU credits.
So it's CPU credits that
decides how much are you allowed
to burst above your baseline performance.
So what is one CPU credit?
Well, one CPU credit is
equal to one virtual CPU,
running at 100% utilization
for one full minute.
There are other combinations
of number of virtual CPUs,
utilization and time that
can equate to one CPU credit.
For example, one CPU
credit is also equal to
one virtual CPU, running
at 50% utilization,
for two minutes.
Or two virtual CPUs
running at 25% utilization
for two minutes.
So these are various combinations
that give you a total of one CPU credit.
We now understood that,
if I have to burst above
my baseline performance,
I need to have positive CPU credits.
So the question is, how do
I get those CPU credits?
How do I earn them?
So each T2 instance
continuously earns a set rate
of CPU credits per hour,
depending on the instance size.
If a T2 instance uses fewer CPU resources
than is required for the
baseline performance,
the unspent CPU credits are accrued
in the CPU credit balance.
Which means if your CPU is running below
the baseline performance,
you are constantly earning CPU credits.
If a T2 instance needs to burst above
the baseline performance level,
it spends the accrued credits.
The more credits a T2
instance has accrued,
the more time it can burst beyond the
baseline performance level.
Now we're gonna talk about
T2 standard instances.
What are these?
Well, just about a few months back,
there was nothing called T2 standard.
It was all T2 instances only.
But the problem was,
T2 instances could only
burst above the baseline
if they had CPU credits.
Now what if your application
or your workload requires
to burst above and you
do not have CPU credits?
You can do nothing about it,
because you do not have CPU credits
and you cannot burst above.
So AWS introduced another
type of T2 instance,
called T2 unlimited,
which we'll talk about
in just about couple of minutes.
So now, the classic T2 instance
was renamed as T2 standard.
So T2 standard is what
was always there and now,
you have another category
called as T2 unlimited.
So what is T2 standard?
A T2 standard instance
is suited for workloads
with an average CPU utilization
that is consistently
below the baseline
performance of that instance.
Essentially what we are trying to say is,
T2 standard instances work
well when your workload
or your application requires
average CPU utilization,
most of the time.
To burst above the baseline,
the instance spends
credits that it's accrued
in its CPU credit balance.
If the instance is running
low on accrued credits,
performance is gradually lowered
to the baseline performance level
so that the instance does not
experience a sharp performance
drop off when its accrued
CPU credit limit is depleted.
So how does all this work?
A T2 standard instance
receives two types of credits.
The first one is an earned credit,
the second one is a launch credit.
When a T2 standard instance
is in a running state,
it is continuously earning a set rate
of earned credits per hour.
When the instance has just started,
it has not earned credits for
a good startup experience.
Therefore to provide a
good startup experience,
it receives a certain number
of launch credits at start.
T2 standard instances get 30
launch credit per virtual CPU
at launch or start.
Launch credits are designed to provide
a good startup experience
to allow instances
to burst immediately after launch,
before they have accrued earned credits.
Now I'm gonna take you to the AWS website
to show you a table.
Alright so I am on the AWS
website and let's take a look
at this table.
On the left-hand side,
we have all the different
instance types of T2.
So you have T2 nano, T2 micro, T2 small,
all the way up to T2 2xlarge.
This column over here shows
you how many CPU credits
they earn per hour.
So if you're running T2 nano for one hour,
it earns three CPU credits.
While T2 micro earns six CPU
credits and all the way up to
81 for T2 2xlarge.
So that's the number of CPU credits
that you can earn per hour.
But what about the maximum?
That is over here.
This column determines
what is the maximum number
of credits that you can
earn in a 24 hour period?
So let's say T2 nano is operating at lower
than the baseline
performance for 24 hours.
So it earns three credits per hour,
and it keeps getting accumulated,
and it can go only to a max of 72 credits
in a 24 hour period.
Similarly T2 micro can only
earn a max of 144 credits
in a 24 hour period.
And so on, all the way up
to 1944 for T2 2xlarge.
Over here we can see the
number of virtual CPUs.
T2 nano, T2 micro and T2 small,
they all have one virtual CPU.
This column over here shows
you the baseline performance.
All along this video we've been talking
about baseline performance.
Well, what is the baseline
performance level?
For T2 nano it's 5% of the CPU.
So if T2 nano is running at
5% or lower CPU utilization,
it will be earning CPU credits.
Remember you earn CPU credits
only when you're performing
at or below the baseline performance.
For T2 micro, the baseline is 10%.
But how 'bout this one.
For T2 medium it is 40% of 200%.
Now you see 200% because
you have two virtual CPUs.
So it's 40% for a combination
of both the virtual CPUs.
And similarly for four virtual CPUs,
it's 90% of 400%.
And for eight virtual
CPUs, it is 135% of 800%,
for the eight virtual CPUs.
I know all this may be sounding
a bit confusing to you.
But the good part is,
all this happens transparently
in the background
without any user intervention.
Moving on, I'm gonna show
you the launch credits,
so I'll take you over here to T2 standard.
I'm gonna leave all those
links in the description
of this video.
And we can see over here
the number of launch credits
each instance type receives.
So we understood that every
instance type receives
30 launch credits per virtual CPU.
So T2 nano, T2 micro and T2 small,
they all have one virtual CPU,
so they all get 30 launch credits.
This one gets 60 because
it has two virtual CPUs
and this one gets 240 because
it has eight virtual CPUs.
Launch credits are essential because
when the EC2 instance boots up,
it might need a performance spike,
and launch credits allow you
to burst above the baseline
to satisfy the performance spike.
Back over here, we'll now
talk about T2 unlimited.
Like I said earlier, sometime back,
it only used to be T2 instances.
But then T2 instances had a problem.
They could not burst above,
if you did not have enough credits.
So they introduced a
new type of T2 instance
called T2 unlimited,
where you can burst above,
even if you do not have credits,
by paying a little money.
So T2 unlimited is a configuration
option for T2 instances
that can be set at launch,
or enabled any time for a
running or stopped T2 instance.
T2 unlimited instances can
burst above the baseline
for as long as required,
which is fantastic.
This enables you to enjoy the
low T2 instance hourly price
and ensures that your
instances are never held
to the baseline performance.
The most interesting part.
The basic T2 hourly instance
price automatically covers
all CPU usage spikes,
if the average CPU utilization
of a T2 unlimited instance
over a 24 hour rolling period,
is at or below the baseline.
Which means if we take the
average of CPU utilization
for a 24 hour period,
and if your average is
less than the baseline,
you don't pay extra even if you did spike
a few times during the day.
If the average is lower than the baseline
for a 24 hour period,
you do not pay extra.
If the average CPU utilization
exceeds the baseline
over a 24 hour period, there
is a flat additional rate,
per vCPU-hour.
How do we set this
option for T2 unlimited?
Let me show you that.
So I'm back over here and I'm
gonna go to the AWS console.
And I'm gonna click on launch instance.
I'm gonna select the first
one which is Amazon Linux AMI.
I'll stick with T2 micro.
Click on next,
and here you'll have the
option to enable T2 unlimited.
So we can just say enable,
and click on next.
Next, you can add a tag if required.
And we can also add a security group.
I'm gonna add this one over here.
Review and launch, and launch.
I'll acknowledge that I
have access to the key pair.
And click on launch instances.
Now let's say,
you decided to turn that option off.
Or let's say, you did not turn it on,
and you wanna turn it on now.
It's very easy.
I'll just wait 'til it
moves to the running state.
Okay so it's now running.
We can select that EC2
instance, we can go to actions,
instance settings, and we can say,
change the T2 unlimited behavior.
So you go to change T2 unlimited,
and you can change the unlimited behavior.
In this case it will stop it
because it is already enabled.
But if it was disabled,
you could turn it on from here as well.
The last thing that I'm gonna show you is,
how to monitor your CPU credit balance.
How do you know what's your balance?
The interesting part is,
you cannot see it on this console.
You have to use CloudWatch in order to see
your CPU credit balance.
Let me show you how to do that.
Okay so I have logged into
another AWS account that I have,
and I've changed my
service over to CloudWatch.
CloudWatch allows you to monitor
your CPU credit utilization
and your CPU credit balance.
The way to do that is by
creating some widgets.
So what I do is, I go
to Dashboards over here.
I already have a dashboard called EC2.
If I click on that,
you will notice that I have some widgets
that monitor my credit
balance and my credit usage.
This one is credit balance and
credit usage for server one,
and this one is for server two.
This is a nice, beautiful
timeline that shows me
the CPU credit usage for server one.
And this one is a stacked graph over here,
which shows me the CPU credit utilization
for server one compared
against server two.
Isn't this really fantastic?
Looks so cool right?
Looks so beautiful.
Now you also have options over
here to change the timeline.
For example if I want to see the values
over a 12 hour period, I can say 12 hours,
and it shows all that data.
How can you create these widgets?
You just say add widget over here,
and you can go to any
one of these options.
These are different types of widgets.
Let's say you wanted a count
widget so you can just select
this one over here.
And click on configure.
The options that you see
over here will depend on
what services of AWS you are using.
For example, right now I'm
using EBS, EC2 and ELB.
So I have these options.
If you're using only EC2,
you might only see EC2.
We are interested in the EC2 metrics only,
so I'm gonna go into that.
I'm gonna click on per-instance metrics,
and depending on the
number of EC2 instances
running in your account,
you might see different values over here.
So I have two instances running,
server one and server two.
I am looking at server
one CPU credit usage.
So I'll check that box over here.
It gets added over here,
and I'm also looking at,
this one which is CPU credit balance for,
not for server two, but for server one.
There you go.
CPU credit balance for server one.
So you can see these values over here,
and you can create your widget.
Once you create your widget,
it sits on your dashboard like what I have
on the screen right now.
I'm gonna make it a little easier for you.
So I'll go to actions.
I'll go to view and edit source.
I'm gonna copy this and
paste it in the description
of this video.
What you need to do is,
you go to CloudWatch,
you go to dashboards,
you do a new dashboard.
Let's call it as My Dashboard.
Create dashboard,
and you go to Actions, view edit source.
Just remove whatever is here.
Paste that and you just need
to change the EC2 instance IDs.
Replace that with your
instance ID and your region.
And poof.
It's gonna be ready
for you just like this.
What I like the most is,
we can actually convert it
into full screen, like this,
and if you want to
realign the whole thing,
you just do a Control
minus and a Control plus.
It just realigns and the
coolest thing is this.
We can change it into a
dark mode and it looks
so cool and beautiful.
Well that's about T2 instances.
I hope you found that interesting.
I'd like to thank you for watching,
and I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.