- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In the last video, we set
up both the target groups,
target group one for the beach servers,
and target group two for the hill servers.
Now, let's start creating
the load balancer.
So we go to load balancers,
create load balancer, and click on create
for application load balancer.
You can give it a name of your choice,
I'm gonna call it as myELB,
and we can choose internet
facing load balancer
or an internal load balancer,
and we understood the differences
when we discussed about
classic load balancers.
Right now, we're gonna receive
traffic from the internet,
so we're gonna do internet
facing load balancer.
This is interesting.
The IP address type can
be IPv4 or dual stack.
If it's IPv4, it only
receives IPv4 traffic.
If you go for dual stack,
it receives both IPv4 and IPv6 traffic.
Right now, I only wanna have IPv4,
and here, we can configure the listeners.
We spoke about listeners
during the classic load balancer topic.
A listener is a configuration
that is looking for
incoming requests from the
internet or from your clients.
In this case, our clients are
gonna be accessing the servers
on port 80, HTTP, so we'll
select the protocol as HTTP
and the port number as port 80.
Next, we need to select
the availability zones
where we want to route the traffic.
You could select one or
you could select multiple.
What I'm gonna do is I'm gonna select
multiple availability zones.
Notice you also have the
option to choose the VPC.
In my case, I only have one VPC.
Having done that, let's
move onto the next step.
Meanwhile, you can also
add some tags over here
for identification purposes.
I'm gonna say next
configure security settings.
Over here, we would not
be configuring anything
because we have selected HTTP
as the listener configuration.
If you go for HTTPS, then we'll
have to configure this part.
Moving on, we can configure
the security groups.
I'm gonna select an
existing security group,
which is HTTP for myELB,
which basically allows port 80 inbound.
Click on next, configure routing.
On step number four, we
need to configure routing,
and as you can see over here,
we need to provide a target group.
The good part is that we
already have one ready.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna select
an existing target group,
and you can select any one of them,
TG1 or TG2.
What I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna go with TG1.
The protocol is selected
as HTTP and the port is 80,
and the target type is instance,
and you'll notice we
cannot select anything
because it's all pre-configured in TG1.
Also notice that the health check protocol
is configured over here, and
the path is also configured.
Again, all this comes
from TG1 configuration.
Down over here, you'll notice
everything is pre-configured,
nothing is editable because
it's all configured over here.
Why do they have it?
Well, if you were configuring
a new target group,
then you would be
configuring all these items.
Right now, it's all pre-configured,
so we can skip this,
and we can go to next, register targets.
You'll notice that the
targets are also selected,
because this target has been registered
in the target group, right?
Click on next review.
We can review all the settings
that we've made so far,
and we can click on create.
Now, we're ready.
So you can see over here,
we have a DNS name for the load balancer,
it's internet facing, it's
an application load balancer,
it's forwarding traffic to
both the availability zones,
and the IP address type is IPv4,
and it is currently being provisioned.
Let's try to do a refresh.
If we went over here to listeners,
we can see we have a listener
configuration over here.
Now, we can try and access
this page over here,
and open a new page, hit enter,
and it says the site cannot be reached,
and that's because it's
still being provisioned.
We can see over here, it's
So we can wait for a little while.
Meanwhile, we can go back
to the target groups,
and let's check what's the status of TG1.
We can select TG1 and
we can go to targets,
and you'll notice over
here it says initial,
target registration is in progress.
So, we need to wait until
this becomes healthy,
and that should happen pretty soon.
Let's do a refresh.
Alright, so now, it's in a healthy state,
which means if we go back over here,
and if we did a refresh,
we can see the IIS page.
Which server is this coming from?
It is coming from the
server in AP south one A,
or server one, because
that's the target group
that has been associated
with the load balancer.
If you go back to load balancers,
we can see over here, under listeners,
that it is forwarding to TG1,
so it is actually coming from server one.
On server one, we know that we
have a folder called beaches,
so if we did this, slash beaches,
we should see that, and if
we click on any one of them,
we have a nice, beautiful
picture of the beach.
But what if we did slash
hills, will it work?
It doesn't, because right now
we are not forwarding traffic to TG2.
That's what we're gonna configure next.
So we'll go back over here,
and we'll edit the load balancer,
so I've selected the load balancer.
Listeners, we're not
gonna add a new listener,
we're going to change the
rules of the listener.
So view and edit rules.
This is where it starts
to get a little confusing
for some people.
View and edit rules.
So the rule is like this,
this is the default rule.
It says if the request,
otherwise not routed,
which means if the request does not match
any other routing parameter,
then forward to TG1.
What we're gonna do is we're
gonna add one more rule,
so I'll click on the plus icon over here,
and I'm gonna say insert a rule,
which will add it on top of this one,
and we can say add condition.
You can do a condition
based on a host header
or a path.
A path is the URL of that request,
and that is what we're gonna do.
So we'll do if the path is,
and it contains the word /hills/.
If the URL contains the word /hills/,
and I'm gonna say add
action, forward it to TG2,
because that's where the
servers for the hills
have been configured.
TG2, click on save, fantastic.
We can now go back and, before
we try to access the URL,
we can go to target groups,
select the second one, TG2,
and you'll notice, now this
one is also an initial.
So if we try to refresh this,
we're still gonna get no response.
I'm actually doing a refresh,
you can see that over here.
It doesn't work because
the server is still being initialized.
So we'll have to wait, in
fact, it's already ready,
it's now in healthy.
So, if we go back over
here, if we did a refresh,
it's still not working,
and I just realized,
the URL is not correct.
It is correct, but I need
to add a trailing slash,
because the listener has
been configured to add
the trailing slash.
So if I put a trailing slash
over here and I hit enter,
now I can see that.
So that's how we configure a target group.
As you can see over here,
based on the requests that we make,
based on the URL or based on
the words contained in the URL,
the traffic is being forwarded
to different servers.
If I did slash beaches,
you'll notice that the
traffic is being forwarded
to a different server,
and if we did slash hills,
like what we tried right now,
the traffic is going
to a different server.
As we can see, this is an
intelligent load balancer.
It has the intelligence to know
where to route the request.
The final piece of the
puzzle is the index.html.
We're gonna put a file called index.html
on both the servers,
and we want to have a
round robin load balancing
when somebody tries to access index.html.
In the next video, we'll
see how to do that.
I'd like to thank you for watching,
and I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.