- Welcome back.
In this video, we're going
to talk about key pairs.
Key pairs are fundamental for EC2,
because key pairs allow
you to login to Unix based
or Linux based EC2 instances,
and for Windows devices,
they allow you to decrypt
and reveal their password.
Amazon EC2 uses public-key
cryptography to encrypt
and decrypt login information.
Public-key cryptography uses a public key
to encrypt a piece of
data, such as a password,
and then, the recipient
uses the private key
to decrypt the data.
The interesting thing about
public-key cryptography is,
anything that is encrypted
with the public key
can only be decrypted with a private key.
The same key which was used for encryption
cannot be used for decryption.
The combination of public and private key
is known as a key pair.
It's two keys together, so
we call them as a key pair.
To login to your instance,
you must create a key pair,
specify the name of the key pair
when you launch the instance,
and then, provide the key pair
when you try to connect to that instance.
On a Linux EC2 instance,
the public-key content
is placed as an entry
within the directory, which
/.ssh/authorized_keys.
This is done automatically at boot time,
and enables you to securely
access your instance
using private keys instead of passwords.
Key pairs can be created
using the Amazon EC2 console,
or you could also use a third-party tool,
and then import the
public key to Amazon EC2.
How do we do that?
I will show you that
in just about a minute.
Very important, Amazon EC2
only stores the public key,
and we store the private key.
That's why we call it as private,
something that we should not
be sharing with anybody else.
Amazon EC2 does not keep a
copy of your private key.
Therefore, if you lose the private key,
there is no way to recover it.
The keys that Amazon EC2 uses
are 2048-bit SSH-2 RSA keys only.
DSA not supported, it has to be RSA.
You can have up to 5000
key pairs per region.
Okay, now let's dive into the console
and see how we can import a new key pair.
All right, so I've logged
into the AWS EC2 console,
and first of all, I'm gonna
go over here to Key Pairs.
So right now, I have one
key pair, which is MyEC2Key.
Remember, key pairs are
regional, which means
the key pair that I have
in the Mumbai region
is not the same that I
have in some other region.
We can verify that.
I'm gonna open another window over here,
and I'm gonna change my region to,
let's say, North Virginia,
and over here, we can see that
we have a different key pair,
which is called as nvkey.
So, that means keypairs are regional.
If you wanted to create a new key pair
within the EC2 console,
you can do Create Key Pair,
or if you wanted to
import your own key pair,
you would use this option.
But before we import it,
we must have it ready.
So, let's do that.
Let's go to the terminal
and create a new key pair.
All right, so I'm here at the terminal.
First of all, I'm going
to elevate my privleges
with sudo su.
Done.
Next, I'm gonna use ssh-keygen -t,
and the name of the
algorithm, which is RSA.
Hit enter.
It says, "Enter the file name."
I'm gonna say Enter.
Do you wanna create a
password for that, no.
Hit enter, perfect, it's done.
Now, I'm gonna navigate into that folder,
which is /var/root/.ssh.
Ls will show me all the files.
So, you have two files.
This one is the public key,
and this one is the private key.
If you want to view the contents of that,
we can do cat id_rsa.pub.
That's the public key.
If you want to view the private key,
you can do cat id_rsa,
and that will give us the private key.
All right, so let's copy that.
Let's copy that public key.
That's the public key, Ctrl-C for copy.
Back over here, to the AWS
console, Import Key Pair.
You can either Browse or
just paste it over here.
I'm gonna call it as mykey.
Paste it over here, click on Import.
Fantastic, it's done.
Now, let's see if it's working.
To do that, I'm gonna
launch a new EC2 instance.
Go to Instances, Launch
Instance, Amazon Linux AMI.
This time, I'm gonna do t2.nano.
You can even use t2.micro.
Click on Next, I'm not gonna
change anything right now.
Just select a security
group which allows SSH.
Review and Launch, Launch, and make sure
you select the new keypair,
which is mykey, and done.
View Instances.
Refresh.
All right, now it is in a running state.
So, I'm gonna copy that public IP address,
come back to the terminal.
I'll first do Clear.
Verify my directory, pwd, perfect.
Now, I'm gonna say ssh
ec2-user@ the public IP -i,
and the private key name is ID_RSA.
Hit Enter, and it says, "Are
you sure you want to continue?"
I'm gonna say yes, and
I'm directly logged in.
We can verify that with
the private IP address
once I'm into 3120238.
Once I'm into 3120238.
So that's how you create
and import a key pair
on a Linux device.
Now, I'll show you how to
do that on a Windows device.
Before that, I'm gonna
terminate this instance.
Terminate.
Okay, and I'll go back
to Key Pairs over here,
and I'll delete this one.
To show you how this
works on a Windows device,
I'm gonna open up a virtual
machine using Virtual Box,
and I have that over here.
On Windows devices, you cannot
directly create a key pair
like how you can do it on Linux devices.
For that, we need a
program called PuTTY Gen.
If you've seen the other
videos on how to connect
to an EC2 instance from
Windows, you already have this,
because we installed this.
Just in case you don't have that,
just search for PuTTY download,
and you should be able to get that.
There are two files.
There's one called PuTTY, and
there's one called PuTTY Gen.
To start with, I'm gonna use PuTTY Gen.
PuTTY Gen, and it says over here,
"Generate a public-private key pair."
So, I'm gonna click on Generate.
Make sure that the algorithm
that you use is RSA.
Now, here's the fun part.
It says, "Please generate some randomness
"by moving the mouse over the blank area."
So, you gotta move your mouse.
And, as you keep moving
that, you'll notice
this keeps moving as well.
All right, so that's done.
This is the public key
that we need to copy
and paste it into EWS.
Where's the private key?
Well, it's over here.
You can say, "Save private key".
"Are you sure you want to
save this without a password?"
Yes.
I'm gonna put it on my desktop,
and I'm gonna call this as my private key.
Click on Save, and you have it over here.
I'm also gonna save my public key.
So, Save Public Key.
Let's call this one as mypubkey,
and click on Save.
And it saved over here.
Next, we need to import this.
So, I'm gonna open up the AWS
console, just refresh it once.
All right, and then, I'll go
down over here to Key Pairs.
I'm gonna import a new key pair.
Let's call it as winkey,
for Windows, maybe.
And then, we need to paste
the public key content.
So, go back over here.
I'm gonna select all of this first.
In fact, I'm gonna select it.
I'll just copy it, go back
over here and paste it,
and click on Import.
All right, once that is done,
we can now try to connect.
To connect, we are not
gonna be using PuTTY Gen,
but we're gonna be using PuTTY.
PuTTY.
Okay, but before that, we need
to launch an EC2 instance.
So, we'll go back to
Instances, Launch Instance,
Amazon Linux AMI.
I'm gonna do t2.micro.
And, I'm just gonna skip all of this.
I'm not changing anything,
I'm just going to add a security group
which allows SSH.
Review and Launch, Launch,
and make sure you select
the right key pair, winkey, and launch it.
View Instances, and we just need to wait
until this becomes running.
So, I'll refresh that.
All right, and I'm gonna copy
the public IP address from here.
Go back to PuTTY.
At this point, you
should know how to login
to a Linux EC2 instance
from a Windows device.
We spoke about this in one
of the earlier lectures.
We'll revise it one more time.
So, in Host Name, we're gonna
say ec2-user@ the public IP.
And then, we open up
SSH, we click on Auth,
we click on Browse, and then,
we select the private key
file, which is my private key.
Open, and we can say Open.
It says, if you trust the file, hit Yes.
I'm gonna say Yes, and you've logged in.
We can verify with the private IP,
which is 172313203.
We have the same one over here, 172313203.
Well, that's about key pairs.
I hope you found it interesting.
Don't forget to turn off your lab.
I'd like to thank you for watching,
and I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.