- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video,
we're gonna talk about
elastic network interfaces.
If you're ready, let's begin.
All right, so what is an
elastic network interface?
Well, an elastic network interface
is a logical networking component in a VPC
that represents a virtual network card.
Think about a physical
desktop or a physical laptop.
Each of these devices has a
physical network interface card,
where we actually plug in that LAN card
or the interface that we
enable to connect to the Wi-Fi.
That's a physical network card.
Similarly, EC2 instances
have a virtual network card,
which is called as the
elastic network interface.
We can create a network interface,
attach it to an instance,
detach it from an instance,
and also attach it back
to another instance,
which makes them very, very flexible.
When you move a network interface
from one instance to another,
network traffic is redirected
to the new instance.
Every instance in a VPC has
a default network interface,
which is called as the
primary network interface
and represented by eth0.
We cannot detach the
primary network interface
from an instance.
We can create and attach
additional network interfaces.
What are the attributes of
an elastic network interface?
Number one,
every elastic network interface
has a primary private IPv4 address
from the IPv4 address range of your VPC.
It may also have one or more
secondary
private IPv4 addresses
from the IPv4 address range of your VPC.
It may also have one Elastic IPv4 address
per private IPv4 address.
It may also have one public IPv4 address,
one or more
IPv6 addresses,
one or more security groups,
also a MAC address,
a source or destination check flag,
which is a flag that
checks if the interface
is the source or
destination of the traffic,
and, additionally, it may
also have a description.
Talking about best practices,
we can attach a network
interface to an instance
when it's running.
This is called as hot attach.
We can also attach it when it is stopped.
It's called as a warm attach.
Or we may also attach it
when the instance is being launched,
which is known as a cold attach.
We can detach secondary network interfaces
when the instance is running or stopped.
However, we cannot detach the
primary network interface,
which is eth0.
The secondary network interface
is represented as ethN,
which is nothing but
eth1, eth2, 3, and so on.
If you attach two or
more network interfaces
from the same subnet to an instance,
you may encounter networking issues
such as asymmetric routing.
So it is not recommended
that you attach two or more interfaces
from the same subnet to the same instance.
Having understood the concepts,
let's look at all of
this on the EC2 console.