- All right.
So I'm here at the AWS EC2 console,
and let's start by
launching an EC2 instance.
So we'll click on Launch Instance.
I'm gonna select the first one,
which is Amazon Linux AMI.
And I'm gonna select
t2.micro, for this one.
Now, over here, you'll notice that,
after this option, which is t2.unlimited,
we only have the option
to add the user data.
But as soon as I change
the subnet, over here,
if I choose a specific subnet,
you'll notice that now I have the option
to add additional network interfaces.
By default, it takes eth0,
which is the default interface,
but if I wanted to add one more,
I can say Add Device, and
we can add one more interface, right?
So this option is available only if
you select the subnet, over here.
Even if we do not add
additional interfaces over here,
we have the option to add it later on.
So we'll leave it at the
default, and we'll continue.
Storage of eight gigs is fine.
We can add some tags, if required.
I'm not doing that right now.
I'm gonna select a security group.
Review and Launch, Launch,
and I'll acknowledge that I
have access to that key pair.
Now, the instance is getting provisioned.
I'm gonna click on this one
and refresh a couple of times.
Meanwhile, we can notice, over here,
that we already have
an IP address assigned,
so we can see that we have
a public IPv4 address,
and we also have a private IPv4 address.
Notice that I have not
received an IPv6 address.
And if I scroll down, I
have one network interface.
If I click on that interface,
I can see the interface ID,
the VPC ID, it says the
attachment status is "attaching".
In fact, if I refresh
this, it's now running.
Let's try that again.
So now it says it is
attached, the attachment date,
the attachment time, private IPv4 address,
public IPv4 address,
and the security group
that has been associated.
Now, I'm gonna click
on this one, over here,
the interface ID, and when I do that,
it moves me to this tab, over here,
which is call as Network Interfaces.
This is the interface, and we can see
that the status is "in-use".
Now, let's try to add
one more IPv4 address
to the same interface.
So you go to Actions, Manage IP Addresses,
and we can say Assign new IP.
At this point, you could
type in an IP address
from that subnet, or
you can say Auto-assign,
which means it will
automatically allocate
an available address,
like what we see on the screen, right now.
Now, if I close this, and if
I just come down, over here,
we can see that we have
two private IP addresses,
one over here, and one over here,
both assigned to the same interface.
If I go back to Instances, over here,
I select a running
instance, we can see that
we have a private IPv4 address,
which is the primary
one, and we also have a
secondary private IPv4 address.
So that means you can have
multiple addresses assigned
to the same interface.
Now, let's change things a little bit.
So we'll go back to Network
Interfaces, all right?
So over here, I notice that
there's a couple of interfaces,
and one of them is available.
I did not create that, right now.
I believe this is from earlier.
I did not do it right now, so
I'm just gonna delete that.
Okay, so we are left
with the one interface.
If we did Manage IP Addresses,
we notice both the IP addresses.
I'm gonna remove this one,
Unassign, Yes, Update.
Now, we only have one
private IPv4 address,
which is mapped to a public IPv4 address.
Let's try to create one more interface.
So you go to Actions, or rather,
we go to Create Network Interface.
We need to select a subnet.
I'm gonna select the same subnet
in which my EC2 instance is present,
which is ap-south-1a.
We can hard-code a private IPv4 address,
or we can say Auto-assign, and then
we must select a security group.
This brings us to a
critical understanding.
All along, we've been talking
about security groups,
and we've been saying that
we are attaching the security group
to the EC2 instance, but the reality is
that security groups are attached
to the network interface,
and the network interface,
in turn, is attached to
that EC2 instance, right?
I'm gonna say Yes, Create,
and we have this second
interface, over here.
Right now, it is not attached,
so it says "available", let's do that.
Attach it to the running instance.
Fantastic.
Now, if I go back to Instances, over here,
and I click on that one, you can see that
we have two private IP addresses,
and both of them show up as primary,
and that's because I have
two network interfaces.
Every private IPv4 address
can be assigned a public IPv4 address.
We'll talk about that in the next video,
when we discuss elastic IPs.
So it is possible to have
multiple network interfaces.
Now, you might be thinking,
what's the use case?
Why should I have multiple
network interfaces?
We can separate production
traffic and management traffic.
I can have all my
management traffic on eth0,
and I can have all my
production traffic on eth1.
Now, let's say I wanted to take down
this instance for maintenance,
and I want to redirect all this
traffic to another instance.
It's really easy.
I just have to detach
it from this instance,
and attach it to another EC2 instance,
and all the traffic
gets redirected, right?
So it gives you so much flexibility.
Now, let's talk about IPv6.
Why don't we have an IPv6 address?
Well, the reason is, the
VPC is not configured
with an IPv6 address range.
So if you're interested in
getting IPv6 IP addresses,
what you need to do is,
you need to go to VPC.
Right now, I only have my default VPC,
so I'm gonna select that, select that VPC.
We can see that the IPv6
CIDR range is empty.
So we go to Actions, over here,
and we say Edit CIDRs, and
we need to add an IPv6 CIDR.
It automatically fills one for you.
We can say close.
Now, we have the IPv6 CIDR, but
there's one more thing to do.
We also must assign IP
addresses, or IP address ranges,
to the subnets, so we go
back over here to Subnets.
We select the first one.
Subnet Actions, Edit IPv6 CIDRs,
and we can say Add IPv6 CIDR.
There you go.
Okay, and we can close that, and
I'll repeat that for the next one.
Subnet Actions, Edit IPv6 CIDRs,
Add IPv6 CIDR, say Yes, and Close.
So at this point, we are now ready
to start assigning IPv6 addresses.
So we go back over here, and let's try
to go back to Network Interfaces,
and let's try to edit the first one.
Actions, Manage IP Addresses, and notice,
now we have that option enabled.
So I'm gonna say Assign
new IP, auto-assign,
Yes, and there you have it.
So I'll close this, and
if I go back to Instances,
now, we should have an IPv6 address.
One last thing before we close this video,
we'll see a document that tells us
how many network
interfaces can be attached
per EC2 instance type.
That is over here.
I'm also gonna leave a
link to this document
in the description of this video.
I'm gonna go down, over here,
to t2.micro, or the t2 instances.
So we can see that, for t2.nano,
you can attach two network interfaces,
and this column tells
you the maximum number
of IP addresses per interface.
This is for IPv4, and this is for IPv6.
So if you look at
t2.micro, excuse me, there,
t2.micro, we can have
two network interfaces,
and two IPv4 addresses per interface,
and two IPv6 addresses per interface.
If you look at t2.large, you can have
three network interfaces,
12 IPv4 addresses
per network interface,
and 12 IPv6 addresses
per network interface.
So that's a lot of flexibility.
Well, that's about network interfaces.
I'd like to thank you for watching,
and I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.