- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video, we're gonna talk about
a very interesting topic
known as Elastic IP Addresses.
Let's begin.
Alright, so what is an Elastic IP Address?
An Elastic IP address
is a static IPv4 address
associated with your AWS account.
To use an Elastic IP address,
you must first allocate
one to your account,
and then associate it with your instance,
or a network interface.
When you associate an Elastic
IP address with an instance,
or its primary network interface,
the instance's public IPv4 address,
if it had one,
is released back into Amazon's pool
of public IPv4 address.
And then we cannot reuse
the public IPv4 address.
So essentially, what it tries to say
is that if your EC2 instance
already had a public IPv4 address,
and you associate it an
Elastic IP with that,
the Elastic IP will
replace your public IP.
And then we don't get that public IP back.
You can dissociate an Elastic IP address
from a resource and reassociate it
with a different resource,
allowing you to mask the failure
of an instance or software.
A disassociated Elastic IP
address remains allocated
to your account until you
explicitly release it.
To ensure efficient use
of Elastic IP addresses,
a small hourly charge is
imposed if an Elastic IP address
is not associated with a running instance,
or if it associated
with a stopped instance,
or an unattached network interface.
In a nutshell, what AWS
is trying to tell you,
is that if you have an Elastic IP,
and you don't use it, we'll charge you.
However, if you're using it,
we're not going to charge you.
While your instance is running,
you are not charged for
one Elastic IP address
associated with the instance,
but you are charged for any
additional Elastic IP addresses
associated with that instance.
So one Elastic IP address
per running EC2 instance is free of cost.
After that, they start charging you.
An Elastic IP address is for
use in a specific region only.
So they are regional components,
or components which are
specific to a region,
just like we understood key pairs.
When you associate an Elastic
IP address with an instance
that previously had a public IPv4 address,
the public DNS host name
of the instance changes
to match the Elastic IP address.
Don't worry if that sounds confusing.
In just about a minute, I'll
show you exactly what I mean.
By default, all AWS accounts are limited
to five Elastic IP addresses per region,
because public internet addresses
are a scarce public resource.
Well, that's about the concepts,
let's look at all of this in action.
So I'm back over here on the AWS console,
and right now I have one Running Instance.
So I'm gonna go over here to Instances,
and we can see that we
have a running Instance.
If I click on that,
I want you to notice
that I have a public IP,
and I also have a public DNS name,
which has the public IP embedded in that.
13.126.62.65 is part of
that public DNS name.
Also notice that I have two private IPs,
and they both belong to
the same network interface,
which is eth0.
Over here you can see that I
do not have any Elastic IP.
So, what is the problem?
Why do we even need an Elastic IP?
Well the problem is this IP over here.
If I stop my EC2 instance,
and start it again,
my public IP will change.
So that means, all existing connections
on this public IP will be terminated,
which is not good.
So I wanna make sure that I
have a consistent IPv4 address
for my server.
And how do I do that?
By using Elastic IPs.
Elastic IPs do not change
because Elastic IPs are not
associated with your instance,
they're associated with your AWS account.
Let's see how to do that.
So over here we have a
tab called Elastic IPs.
You can see that I do not have
any addresses in this region.
Let's go and allocate one.
So I'm gonna say Allocate new address,
and click on Allocate.
So I have a new Elastic IP.
I'm gonna click on Close.
But right now it is not
attached or associated
with an instance.
So we'll go to Actions,
and we'll click on Associate address.
There's two ways to do this.
You may associate it with an Instance,
or with a network interface.
If I select Instance,
I have that running Instance over here,
and remember Elastic IPs are mapped
to an existing private IP address.
So in this case,
since I have two private IP
address on that Instance,
I can select any one of them.
Or, I could go to Network Interface,
and I can select the Interface
to which I want to associate.
Right now, in this case I
only have one Interface.
But right now I'm gonna
associate it with an Instance.
So I'll select that Instance,
and I'll select any one of them.
I'll click on Associate,
it's done.
And now when I go back to Instances,
you'll notice that the public IP matches
the Elastic IP,
13.126.255.143.
Also notice that the
DNS name has now changed
to reflect that public IP address.
Sorry, the Elastic IP address.
We could associate more
than one Elastic IP address,
because Elastic IPs are
mapped to private IPs, right?
So this one is already mapped to this one,
but I could associate one
more Elastic IP to this one,
if I wanted to.
The good part about Elastic IPs is that
if you want to redirect your
traffic to another Instance,
you could simply remove this,
and associate with another Instance,
and all the traffic gets
routed over to that Instance.
Well, that's the simple
concept of Elastic IPs.
They allow you to have a fixed,
or a static public IPv4 address.
That's it for this video.
Just make sure that you shut
down your EC2 Instances,
and also make sure that
you release your Elastic IP
back to the pool,
because if you do not do that,
they will start charging you for that.
So you go back to Elastic IPs,
Actions, Dissociate the address.
That's not the only step.
We have to go back to Actions,
and release it back to the pool.
Now we're done,
and we can shut down
that Instance as well.
Well, that's it for this video.
I'd like to thank you for watching,
and I'll catch you in the
next video, thank you.