- [Instructor] Welcome back, in this video
we're gonna talk about
placement groups, let's begin.
All right, so what do we
mean by a placement group?
Well, before I take you into
the technical definition
of what a placement group
is, I'm gonna put it
to you in really simple words.
In simple words, a placement group is
just a logical grouping
of your EC2 instances, it
just defines how your EC2
instances are logically grouped.
There are two different
types of groupings,
essentially two different
types of placement groups.
Each of them has a certain way
of grouping the EC2 instances
and gives a different output, right?
But in simple words, a placement group is
just a logical grouping
of your EC2 instances.
Now let's look at the
technical definition.
So launching instances in a
placement group determines
how instances are placed
on the underlying hardware.
There are two strategies for
creating a placement group.
The first one is called -s cluster.
It clusters your instances
into a low-latency group
within a single Availability Zone.
That's the limitation for cluster.
Your instances have to be grouped
within a single Availability Zone.
If you choose the spread
strategy, it spreads
your instances across
distinct underlying hardware.
The interesting part is there is no charge
for creating a placement group.
Let's talk a little bit more
about cluster placement groups.
A cluster placement group
is a logical grouping
of your instances within a
single Availability Zone.
Placement groups are
recommended for applications
that benefit from low network latency,
high network throughput, or both.
A good example for this would
be stock market applications,
where your stock prices
keep changing all the time,
in fact, almost every second.
That's a classic example of where
you might want to use a placement group.
A cluster placement group cannot span
multiple Availability Zones.
It is recommended to
launch the required number
of instances in a single launch request
and also to use the same instance type
for all instances in a
cluster placement group.
Essentially, what it is trying to say is,
let's say you want to have three instances
in a placement group, it is best to launch
all three instances
within a single request.
What happens is, let's say
you launch two instances first
into a placement group and you try
to add one more instance,
there are chances
that you might receive an
insufficient capacity error.
To avoid this, it is
recommended that you launch
all required instances with
a single launch request, and
it is also recommended that
you use the same instance type.
Maybe all three of them are m4.large,
or maybe all three of them
are some other instance type.
Essentially, they are all
the same instance type.
The maximum network throughput
between two instances
in a cluster placement group is limited
by the slower of the two instances.
For applications with high
throughput requirements,
choose an instance type with 10-Gbps
or 25-Gbps network connectivity.
And I'll show you exactly
how you can find out
what is the throughput
of your EC2 instance.
So let's say I'm launching two instances
within a cluster placement group.
One of them has 10-Gbps capacity
and the other one has 25-Gbps capacity.
What's gonna be the network throughput
between both these instances?
It is equal to the slower
of the two instances.
In this case, the slower one is 10-Gbps
and that will be the throughput
between both the instances.
All right, now let's talk
about spread placement groups.
A spread placement group
is a group of instances
that are each placed on
distinct underlying hardware.
So if you choose the option
called spread placement group,
all your instances of the
placement group will be placed
on distinct underlying hardware,
which means the physical servers on
which the instances are created
will be totally different.
Launching instances in
a spread placement group
reduces the risk of simultaneous
failures that might occur
when instances share the
same underlying hardware.
Imagine this, you had three EC2 instances
within a placement group and
all the three instances are
on the same underlying hardware.
So if the underlying hardware fails,
all your instances fail,
but that does not happen
with spread placement groups.
All your instances will
be on separate physical
underlying hardware,
which means even if one
of the hardware goes down,
it's just one of the instances
in that placement group
that will be affected.
The remaining will be just fine.
Spread placement groups are suitable
for mixing instance types or
launching instances over time.
This was a limitation with
cluster placement groups.
With cluster placement
groups, the recommendation was
that you should launch
all of them together
and you should have
the same instance type.
Over here, that's not the case.
Spread placement groups are
recommended for applications
that have a small number
of critical instances
that should be kept
separate from each other.
A spread placement group can span
multiple Availability Zones
and you can have a max
of seven running instances per
Availability Zone per group.
Let's now talk about some
rules for placement groups.
Number one, the name you specify
for a placement group must be unique
within your AWS account for that region.
Not all instance types are
available for launching
into a placement group,
and I will talk about
which of those are not supported.
Placement groups cannot
be merged, for example,
let's say I have one placement
group of two instances
and another placement
group of three instances.
If I wanted to merge all of
them to make five instances
within one placement group,
that would not be possible.
If I had to bring all the five instances
into the same placement group,
I can shut down the two instances
which are in the same placement group,
and launch in the other one
which has three instances.
An instance can be launched
into one placement group
at a time, it cannot span
multiple placement groups.
All right, having understood the concepts,
let's look at some of this in action.
All right, so I'm here at the AWS console
and I'm first gonna navigate into EC2.
Before we launch an instance
into a placement group,
we must first create a placement group,
and we can do that from
here, Placement Groups.
Right now, I do not
have a placement group.
I'm gonna start by creating
one, Create Placement Group.
And I'm gonna call it as MyPlacementGroup,
and I'm gonna choose
the strategy as Cluster.
We understood that when you
choose the cluster strategy,
all of your instances have to be
within the same Availability Zone.
I'm gonna click on Create, and that's it.
Now when you launch the instance,
when you go back to Instances over here,
I'm going to click on Launch Instance
and I'm gonna select Amazon Linux AMI.
Now here is where you can
see your network performance.
So you can see that some of them support
up to 10 Gbps, while some of
them support up to 25 Gbps.
So you can see that over here.
Now, not all of your
instance types are available
for launching into placement groups.
For example, if I tried
t2.micro and click on Next,
ideally you should get
that option over here.
But I do not have that option,
because t2.micro cannot be
launched into a placement group.
So I'm gonna show you a document
which shows what are the instance types
which are allowed for placement groups.
All right, so this is the document
and I'm gonna be leaving a link
to this document in the resources section.
Over here, we can see that these
are the only instance types
that can be launched
into a placement group.
And we can see that, in general purpose,
we do not have the t2 instance class,
which is why we cannot use that.
So if we wanted to try it, we
could probably try m4.large.
So let's go back to the console
and let's go back over here.
Let's say Launch Instance,
Amazon Linux AMI,
and this time I'm gonna go with m4.large.
Click on Next, and over
here we have the option
that says Add instance to placement group.
We can select an existing placement group.
This is the one that we created.
Or we could also create
a new placement group.
So that's the concept of placement groups.
What's the bottom line?
The bottom line is that
placement groups are
just a logical grouping
of your EC2 instances.
There are two strategies
that you can follow,
cluster and spread, each of
them has different features.
Why would you want to
put your EC2 instances
into a placement group?
Well, by doing that you
get high network throughput
and low network latency.
That's about placement groups.
I'd like to thank you for watching,
and I'll catch you in the
next video, thank you.