- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video, we'll talk
about EC2 instance lifecycle.
Let's begin.
An EC2 instance has several
stages as part of the lifecycle.
And the first stage is
known as instance launch.
When an EC2 instance is launched,
it enters the first state,
which is called as the pending state.
The instance type that you
specified at launch time
determines the hardware
of the host computer
for your instance.
Essentially, what it is saying is,
depending on the instance
type, and the instance size,
the hardware of the
underlying physical computer
will be determined.
Once the instance is ready,
it enters the running state.
When the instance enters
the running state,
you are billed for every second,
with a one-minute minimum,
that you keep the instance running,
even if the instance remains idle
and you do not connect to it.
This is very important to understand.
The minimum billing cycle for
an EC2 instance is one minute
and after your one minute is over,
it's a per-second billing.
Even if you do not use it, even
if you do not connect to it,
you're certainly gonna
get charged for that.
Next is instance start and stop.
When you stop your instance,
it enters the stopping state
and then it enters the stopped state.
Instance usage or data transfer fees,
are not charged after
the instance has stopped.
However, storage costs for
EBS volumes are applied.
When the instance is in the stopped state,
certain attributes, such as
instance type, can be modified.
When the instance is started,
it, again, enters the pending state
and the instance may have been
moved to a new host computer,
which means, when you
stop your EC2 instance
and when you start it again,
the instance may have moved
to a different physical host.
If your instance is running in EC2-VPC,
it retains its private IPv4 address
and IPv6 address, if it had one.
What is EC2-VPC?
Well, all the new AWS accounts
have the concept of VPC.
Longtime back or, maybe a few years back,
AWS did not have the concept of VPC.
Those accounts are called as EC2-Classic.
But all accounts which
have the concept of a VPC
are called as EC2-VPC.
Most likely, the account that
you're using is also EC2-VPC.
So, if your instance
is running in EC2-VPC,
it will retain its private
IPv4 and IPv6 address
when you stop and start it.
Instance reboot.
When an instance is rebooted,
it remains on the same host computer.
It also maintains its public
DNS name, private IP address,
and any data on its
instance store volumes.
In one of the earlier lectures,
when we spoke about
instance store volumes,
we understood that instance store volumes
are used for temporary storage.
You will lose your data if
your instance has been stopped,
it has been terminated or if
the underlying hardware fails.
And we also understood that,
if your EC2 instance is rebooted,
the data in the instance
store volume will persist.
Rebooting an instance does not start
a new instance billing period.
Per-second billing continues
without a further
one-minute minimum charge.
Let's talk about instance retirement.
An instance is scheduled to be retired
when AWS detects a failure
on the underlying hardware
that cannot be repaired.
If your instance is
scheduled for retirement,
you will receive an
email prior to the event
with the instance ID
and the retirement date.
When an instance reaches its
scheduled retirement date,
it is stopped or terminated by AWS.
If your instance root device
is an Amazon EBS volume,
the instance is stopped
and you can start it again at anytime.
However, if your instance root device
is an instance store volume,
the instance is terminated
and cannot be used again.
I'm gonna take you to the AWS console
and show you exactly where
you get that notification.
And back over here to the AWS console
and I'm gonna navigate
to the EC2 dashboard.
If your instance is
scheduled for retirement,
you will see that over here
in the Scheduled Events.
This is the place where
they'll send you a notification
that your instance is about to be retired.
Of course, they will
also send you an email
with the instance ID
and the retirement date.
And you can also see it
on the console over here.
Back over here, let's talk
about instance termination.
When the instance is terminated,
the status changes to
shutting down or terminated
and you stop incurring
charges for that instance.
After the instance is terminated,
it remains visible in the
console for a short while
and then the entry's
automatically deleted.
Terminated instances cannot be recovered.
Well, that's about the
EC2 instance lifecycle.
I'd like to thank you for watching
and I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.