- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video, we're gonna talk about
a very interesting topic known
as EC2 instance metadata.
This lecture requires you
to perform some activities
on an EC2 instance,
so I'm gonna recommend you
to launch an EC2 instance,
preferably a Windows and a Linux instance,
and you do it side by side with me.
Let's start.
So, what is instance metadata?
Well, instance metadata is
data about your instances
that you can use to configure or manage
the running instances.
How do we get that data?
By accessing a specific URI,
and the URI is on your screen,
http://169.254.169.254/latest/meta-data/.
When you make an HTTP request
to retrieve instance metadata,
you're not billed for that.
Well, that's the conceptual part.
Let's look at all of this in action.
Alright, so I'm here on the AWS console,
and as you can see, I have
two running instances.
Over here, I have an Amazon Linux AMI,
which is called as LinuxServer,
and over here, I have
a Windows EC2 instance.
I'm gonna first start with this one.
I've already connected to that instance,
so I'm gonna open up my terminal.
Alright, as you can see,
I've already logged into my EC2 instance.
How do we use that URI
to get metadata off this EC2 instance?
It's really simple, we're
gonna use a pre-installed tool
called as cURL.
So you start with curl, and
then you type in that URI.
Okay, so that's curl space
http://169.254.169.254/latest/meta-data.
Remember, I told you that trailing slash,
if you don't have it, it doesn't work.
So, make sure that you
have that trailing slash.
Now when I hit enter, you can see that
there's a bunch of
information that we can query.
For example, if I wanted
to know what is the AMI ID,
I can append this with
ami-id, which is from here.
Let's try that, hit enter,
and that's the AMI ID
that I'm using right now.
Let's say I wanted to view my instance ID,
so I can remove that
and type in instance-id,
and there I have it.
Let's say I wanted to
view my instance type.
So I can hit the up arrow,
and say instance-type,
and we can see that it's a t2 micro.
How about the mac address?
So, I'll hit the up
arrow, and I'll say mac.
How about the public IP address?
Public-ipv4, and there
you have the public IP.
We can also try the public host name.
Right, so you have the public host name.
That's how we can query and retrieve
the EC2 instance metadata.
It's really simple.
If you see something like this,
which has a trailing slash,
that means you have further
categories beyond this.
So, for example, if I
did metadata-network/
you can see that there's one
more, which is interfaces.
So we can try that.
Slash.
And then you have something called macs.
So, m-a-c-s slash.
Right now, we only get one mac address,
because on this EC2 instance,
I have only one network
interface, which is ET80.
If I had more network interfaces,
I would receive more mac addresses.
In fact, one mac address per interface.
That's how you do it on a
Linux or a Unix EC2 instance.
How do we do this on Windows?
To show you that,
I've already logged in to
a Windows EC2 instance.
I have it over here.
So what I have done is
I've logged in and I've
opened up Internet Explorer.
Now, the URI needs to be
typed into the browser,
so it's gonna be
http://169.254.169.254/latest,
and you can see that I've
already tried it before,
/meta-data, don't forget
the trailing slash,
and hit enter.
And now, we have that
exact same information.
If I wanted to view the AMI ID,
I can say ami-id, hit
enter, and we can see that.
If you wanted to go back,
hit the back button,
and you can try some of the categories,
like, for example, maybe public keys.
And that's the key pair
that I'm using, right?
So, that's about EC2 instance metadata.
Simply put, it is data
about your EC2 instance,
which can be used by other
applications or third-party tools
that you might be using
in your organization.
What's important is that URI.