- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video, we are going to deep dive
into the concept of EBS volumes.
Let's begin.
Alright, so what do we
mean by an EBS volume?
Amazon Elastic Block Store,
also known as Amazon EBS,
provides block level storage volumes
for use with EC2 instances.
EBS volumes are highly
available and reliable
storage volumes that can be attached to
any running instance that is
in the same availability zone.
Think of EBS volumes like hard drives.
We usually attach a hard drive
to a laptop or a desktop.
In a similar way, we
can attach EBS volumes
to amazon EC2 instances.
The one thing that we must remember
is that if you want to attach
a volume to an EC2 instance,
they must be in the
same availability zone.
Amazon EBS is recommended when data
must be quickly accessible and requires
long-term persistence.
EBS volumes behave like raw,
unformatted block devices.
Like I said, think of it as a hard drive.
You can create a file system
on top of these volumes,
or use them in any other way
you would use a block device
like a hard drive.
So we can install an operating
system on top of that,
we can even put a database
on top of that, et cetera.
EBS volumes can be used as primary storage
for data that requires frequent updates,
such as the system drive for an instance
or storage for a database application.
What's very interesting is
that EBS volumes persist
independently from the running
life of an EC2 instance.
After a volume is attached to an instance,
it can be used like any
other physical hard drive.
What does it mean that EBS
volumes persist independently?
Well, if you have a running EC2 instance,
and you shut down that
instance, it's not necessary
that you have to lose that EBS volume.
You can terminate your EC2
instance and still retain
your EBS volume.
EBS volumes are flexible.
You can dynamically increase the size,
modify the provisioned IOPS capacity,
and change the volume type
on live production volumes.
IOPS stands for Input Output Per Second.
So we can do all of
these stuff on the fly.
We can change the size of the volume,
we can change the
performance of that volume,
and we can also change
the type of the volume
and I'm gonna show you all
of this in the next video.
In this video, we'll just discuss
the concepts and features,
in the next video, we'll see
all of this live in action.
Let's now talk about data
availability of EBS volumes.
When you create an EBS volume
in an availability zone,
it is automatically
replicated within that zone
to prevent data loss due to failure
of any single hardware component.
So whenever we create a new EBS volume,
it is automatically being
replicated in the background
by EWS, to provide high data
availability and resiliency.
After creating a volume,
it can be attached to
any EC2 instance in the
same availability zone.
That means if you have an EC2 instance
in, let's say, AB South 1A,
you can attach a volume only if the volume
also belongs to AB South 1A.
After you attach a volume,
it appears as a native
block device similar to a hard drive.
At that point, the instance can interact
with the volume just as it
would with a local drive.
The instance can format the
EBS volume with a file system,
such as ext3, and then
install applications as well.
Moving on, an EBS volume
can be attached to only one
instance at a time within
the same availability zone.
Just like we have a hard
drive, which can only be
attached to one desktop or one laptop,
similarly, an EBS volume
can only be attached
to a single EC2 instance.
However, multiple volumes can be attached
to a single instance,
just like we can attach
multiple hard drives to a single computer.
Multiple volumes attached to
a device can also be striped
for increased input and output
and throughput performance,
which means multiple volumes
can be logically combined
to appear like a single,
larger EBS volume.
Moving on, let's talk about
data persistence on EBS volumes.
An EBS volume is an off-instance
storage that can persist
independently from the
life of an instance.
You continue to pay for the volume usage
as long as the data persists.
EBS volumes that are attached
to a running instance
can be detached from that
instance with their data intact
when that instance is terminated.
If your EC2 instance is terminated,
that does not mean your EBS
volume also has to terminate.
The volume can then be
reattached to a new instance,
enabling quick recovery of data.
By default, EBS volumes that
are created and attached
to an instance at launch are
deleted when that instance
is terminated, and we saw this when we
launched an EC2 instance.
When you launch an EC2
instance, on step number four,
we are required to add an EBS volume
for the root device storage.
And we've also saw that
there is a check box
which says, "delete on termination."
That's the default check box.
When the EC2 instance gets terminated,
the volume also gets terminated.
We could uncheck that, and that would mean
the EC2 instance is
independent from the volume.
This behavior can be modified
when launching the instance,
causing the volume to persist even after
the instance is
terminated, and enables you
to attach the volume to another instance.
If you are using an EBS-backed instance,
well, what does an
EBS-backed instance mean?
An EC2 instance whose root
volume is an EBS volume.
So if you're using an EBS-backed instance,
you can stop and restart that instance
without affecting the data
stored in the attached volume.
The volume remains attached throughout
the stop and start cycle.
The data persists on the volume
until the volume is deleted explicitly.
The physical block storage
used by deleted EBS volumes
is overwritten with zeroes
before it is allocated
to another account, which means
if you have an EBS volume,
and you delete that, that space
which was reserved for you
may be used for creating
another EBS volume
for another customer.
But before AWS does
that, the physical space
used by your volume is
overwritten with zeroes
to make sure all of your data
has been completely erased.
When dealing with sensitive
data, it is recommended
to encrypt the EBS volume.
Let's now talk about data
encryption on EBS volumes.
EBS volumes can be encrypted
to meet a wide range
of data-at-rest encryption requirements
for regulated or audited
data and applications.
Amazon EBS encryption uses
256-bit advanced encryption
standard algorithms,
also known as AES-256,
and an Amazon-managed key infrastructure,
also known as KMS.
The encryption occurs
on the server that hosts
the EC2 instance, providing encryption of
data-in-transit from the EC2 instance
to Amazon EBS storage.