- [Instructor] Let's now
talk about EBS volume types.
Amazon EBS volumes fall
into two categories
based on performance
characteristics and pricing.
Number one, we have SSD-backed volumes.
These are optimized for
transactional workloads
involving frequent read
or write operations
with small I/O size,
where the dominant
performance attribute is IOPS,
input/output per second.
Number two, we have HDD-backed
volumes or hard disk drives,
optimized for large streaming workloads
where throughput is a better
performance measure than IOPS.
We go for SSD volumes when we are looking
for a very high number of IOPS,
whereas we go for HDD-backed volumes
when we are looking at throughput
as a performance attribute.
Talking about SSD volumes,
we have two types.
We have general purpose SSD,
and then we have provisioned IOPS.
With general purpose SSD, the volume size
can be between 1 GB and 16 TB.
While for provisioned IOPS,
it can be 4 GB to 16 TB.
The max IOPS for general
purpose is 10,000,
which means 10,000
input/output per second,
whereas for provisioned
IOPS, the max can be 32,000.
You see that we also have differences
in terms of throughput volume,
and the dominant performance
attribute is IOPS
for both of them,
which means we use IOPS
as a comparison attribute
for SSD volumes.
Use cases, general purpose
is suited for most workloads,
boot volumes, virtual desktops,
low latency interactive applications,
dev and test environments.
While provisioned IOPS is suitable
for critical business applications
that require sustained IOPS performance,
large database workloads such
as MongoDB, Cassandra, etc.
Talking about HDD volume types,
we have a couple of them.
Number one is throughput optimized
and number two is cold HDD.
The volume size is the same, 500 GB,
all the way up to 16 TB.
The max IOPS is 500 for
throughput optimized,
and 250 for cold HDD.
You can see that there's a
difference in max throughput
per volume as well.
The dominant attribute over
here is MiBs per second
or throughput.
The use case for throughput optimized
is streaming workloads
that require consistent,
fast throughput at a low price,
as well as big data, data
warehouses, log processing, etc.
Please keep in mind this
cannot be a boot volume.
Remember in the video where
we launched an EC2 instance?
We saw that the root
volume did not allow us
to select an HDD-backed volume.
Use cases for cold HDD are
throughput-oriented storage
for large volumes where data
is infrequently accessed
and lowest storage cost is important.
Again, it cannot be a boot volume.
The last one is EBS magnetic,
it is also known as
previous generation HDD.
Magnetic volumes are
backed by magnetic drives,
suited for workloads where
data is accessed infrequently,
and where low cost storage
for small volume sizes is important.
Over here, you have volume sizes from 1 GB
all the way up to 1 TB and
the max IOPS is 40 to 200.
Well, that's it for this video.
I'd like to thank you for watching,
and I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.