- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video, we're gonna
do some hands on stuff
with EBS Volumes.
If you are ready, let's begin.
All right, I'm here at the AWS console
and as you can see right now,
I do not have any running EC2 instances.
First of all, I'm gonna
launch an EC2 instance.
I'm gonna click on Launch Instance
and I'm gonna select the first one,
which is Amazon Linux AMI
and I'm gonna select the size as t2_micro.
I'm gonna select Next for
Configure Instance Details.
Over here, I'm not gonna make any changes
and I'm gonna move on to the next one,
which is Add Storage.
Over here, we can see that by default,
it has a Root volume
and the size of the root
volume is eight gigs.
If we launched a Windows EC2 instance,
the size of the root
volume would be 30 gigs.
Over here, we can select the volume type.
Root volumes allow only three volume types
out of the five that we
discussed the last video
and here you can see the IOPS,
which is input/output per second
and here we have a check box
that says Delete on Termination.
Having this turned on means that
when you terminate your EC2 instance,
the volume will also be terminated.
However, if you'd like
to retain the volume,
even if the EC2 instance
has been terminated,
you can uncheck this box over here.
Let's do that right now.
Also, notice that you can
add a new volume over here.
We can select the size of that new volume
and notice that now,
we have all the five
volume types available.
We can also choose to
delete on termination
and we can also encrypt
this volume over here.
Right now, I'm just gonna
leave it at the Root volume
and I'm gonna select Next.
I'm gonna add a security group.
I'm gonna select any one of them,
maybe this one, review and
launch and click on Launch.
I'll acknowledge that I
have the key pair with me
and I'll click on Launch Instances.
I go down over here and
I'll click on View Instances
and we can see that the EC2
instance is being provisioned.
While this is happening,
let's go down over here
to Volumes and we can see that
the volume appears over here as well.
Here's the volume ID and
the size is eight gigs
and notice over here, it
says the state is in-use.
That means, it is actually
attached to an EC2 instance.
If you're not sure of the EC2 instance
to which it is attached,
you can go down over here
and we can click on the instance ID
or we can do it from here as well.
So if I click on this one over here,
it takes me back to Instances
and this is the instance
that we launched right now.
Now, I'm gonna try and
terminate this EC2 instance,
Actions, Instance State, Terminate,
Yes, Terminate.
Let's go back to Volumes
and see what happens to that volume.
It can take about a minute or so
for the EC2 instance to terminate
so while that is happening,
let's see how we can create
an additional volume.
So, I'm gonna click on
Create Volume over here.
Notice we have all the
five types to choose from.
I'm gonna select the first one,
which is General Purpose SSD.
We can see that the
minimum has to be one gig
and the max can be 16 gigs.
For now, I'm gonna keep it as two gigs
and we can select the availability zone.
Depending on the region
that you selected over here,
you can select the availability zones.
So in Mumbai, we only have a
couple of availability zones.
If you wanted to create the volume
from an existing snapshot,
we can select that snapshot from here
or the Snapshot ID from here.
Notice we also have the
option to encrypt this volume.
If I select this option,
I can select the encryption key as well.
I can use the default encryption key
or I can also use my own
custom encryption key.
Right now, I'm gonna say no to this.
I don't wanna encrypt that
and we can also add tags to the volume
for identification and filtering.
I'm gonna say Create Volume and
the volume has been created.
We have the Volume ID.
So at this point, you can see that
there is a couple of volumes.
Now notice the first one.
This was from that EC2 instance.
It has now changed to available
because the EC2 instance
to which it was attached
has now been terminated
and since we did not check that box,
which said Delete on Termination,
the volume is still available
even though the EC2 instance
has been terminated.
The good part is, now we
can attach this volume
to another EC2 instance.
Meanwhile, the second
volume has also moved in
to the available state.
Let's say we wanted to modify
the size of that volume.
Let's say this is two gigs
and I wanted to make it four gigs.
How would I do that?
So, you go to Actions and
you can say Modify Volume.
The current size is two gigs.
So I can change it to maybe four gigs
but notice what happens if I do one gig.
It says, "The size of a
volume can only be increased,
not decreased."
This is a very important concept.
Volumes can only be increased in size
but not decreased in size.
How about moving volumes
across availability zones?
For example, you can see that this volume
was created in ap-south-1a.
If I wanted to move this to ap-south-1b,
can I do that?
The answer is not directly.
There is no option
to change the availability zone from here.
So, what we would have to do is,
we would have to create
a snapshot of this volume
and then we would have
to restore that snapshot
to another availability zone.
And we'll talk about snapshots
in one of the upcoming videos.
If we wanted to attach this
volume to an EC2 instance,
we can use this option over
here called Attach Volume
and we can select the
EC2 instance from here.
Right now, I do not have
any running EC2 instance.
Please keep in mind, this
is not the only step.
Over here, you're just
mapping it to an EC2 instance
but then we also need to make some changes
on the instance itself
like mounting the volume
and we'll understand that
in the upcoming videos.
If you wanted to check the statistics,
we have those statistics over here.
We can see the Volume ID, the
size, when was it created,
the volume type, what's
the availability zone, etc.
If you wanted to delete a volume,
we can delete that from here.
However, if it is attached
to an EC2 instance,
you would not be able to
delete it till you detach it
so you can detach it from here.
Right now it's not attached
so it's grayed out over here.
All right, so that's about EBS Volumes.
I hope you enjoyed this video.
I'd like to thank you for watching
and I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.