- [Narrator] Welcome back.
In this video we'll
understand how to attach
an EBS volume to a Linux EC2 instance.
To get started, I'm first gonna
dive into the AWS console.
Alright, I'm over here at the AWS console,
and you can see that I already
have a running EC2 instance
and the AMI for that is Amazon Linux AMI.
When I go to volumes,
you can see that I have an 8 gig volume,
which is attached to that Linux instance.
And I'm gonna create a new one.
So I'm gonna click on new volume,
and I'm gonna choose the type as GP2,
which is General Purpose SSD,
and I'm gonna give the size as 1 gig,
and I'm gonna give the availability zone
as the same availability
zone of my EC2 instance,
which is ap-south-1a.
Let's do create volume.
Now that the volume has been created,
I'm gonna do a refresh,
and we can see that the volume
is now in an available state.
To attach the volume, we'll
go to actions, attach volume,
and I'm gonna select my EC2 instance,
and notice that the device
is shown as /dev/sdf.
Also notice that it gives
you a warning over here
that newer Linux kernels
may rename your devices
to /dev/xvdf, so when you
log in to your EC2 instance,
the device will be shown
like this: /dev/xvdf.
Let's do Attach, so now it is in use.
Next I'm gonna log in to my EC2 instance
and I've already done that.
You can see over here
I've already logged in.
First of all, we need to
verify how many volumes
have been attached to this EC2 instance.
And to do that we have a
command which is lsblk.
Lsblk.
I'm gonna hit enter.
And over here we can see that this is
the root volume /vxda1 which is 8 gigs.
And this is the volume that we created,
/vdf which is 1 gig in size.
Notice that /xvda1 has a mount point of /.
Slash indicates that it
is mounted to the root
of the Linux file system hierarchy.
However, this volume does
not have a mount point.
So we need to mount this volume
before we can start using that.
But before we mount the volume,
we need to create a file
system on that volume.
However, before doing that,
we want to verify if there is
already an existing file system or not.
The way to do that is
sudo file -s /dev/xvdf.
Before we run this command,
I also want you to notice that
the output of this command
does not have /dev on it.
It only shows you this portion.
It hides the /dev part.
So we need to type that in explicitly.
Sudo file -s /dev/xvdf.
I hit enter, and if you
see something like this,
just data, that means there
is no file system on it.
We can try the same thing
with the first volume, xvda1,
and you'll notice that there
is some file system on it.
Ext4 is the file system type.
If we had created the new
volume from an existing snapshot
it would already have a
file system on top of that.
But right now we have
created a blank volume.
That's why we do not have a file system.
So let's go ahead and
create a new file system.
I'm gonna do sudo mkfs -t.
The file system type
I'm gonna use as ext4,
and the volume is /dev/xvdf.
Hit enter,
and we can see that the file
system has been created.
Next we need to create a
directory for mounting it.
So I'm gonna do sudo mkdir,
and we can call it whatever we like.
I'm gonna call it as mp
just for mount point.
Hit enter.
We can do ls to verify that
the directory has been created.
We can see that over here.
Next we're gonna mount that.
So sudo mount /dev/xvdf
and the mount point, which is mp.
Hit enter, and it has now been mounted.
To verify this we could, again, do lsblk.
And we can see that over here,
/dev/xvdf has been
mounted to this directory.
At this point we can
start using the volume.
However, there's a problem.
If you reboot the EC2 instance,
you would have to repeat
the process again.
So we wanna make sure that every time
the EC2 instance reboots,
it automatically gets mounted.
The way to do that is to make a
modification to the fs tab file.
So I'm gonna change my directory to /etc,
and I'm gonna do ls.
You can see that we have a file
over here which is called as fstab.
We can view the contents of
that file with cat fstab.
This is what it has right now.
Before we modify this file
we wanna take a backup.
This is a very critical file.
So first of all I'm gonna take a backup.
I'm gonna do sudo cp for copy.
Fstab is the original file name,
and I'm gonna copy it into
another file called as fstab dot,
maybe old or maybe backup,
whatever you'd like to call it.
Hit enter.
Let's do ls to verify.
So we can see that now we have fstab.old,
which will contain the
original contents of this file.
Now we can start modifying this file.
So I'm gonna do sudo, and you
can use your favorite editor.
I'm gonna use vi fstab.
Hit enter.
I'm gonna do insert, which will
allow me to edit this file.
And we need to add a new line over here.
Alright, so I'm gonna
start off with /dev/xvdf
and the mount point name, which is /mp.
The file system type, which is ext4.
And the last three values
that you see over here.
This one over here indicates
the file system mount options.
This one is the dump
frequency of the file system,
and this one represents the order
of the file system
checks done at boot time.
If you're not sure what to put over here,
you can use these values
that I'm typing in right now.
Default, nofail, this one
is 0, and this one is 2.
I'm gonna escape first, :wq!, hit enter.
And I'm just gonna verify
that with cat fstab
just to make sure that the
changes have been saved.
And we can see that the
new entry has been added.
Before we finish off,
it's important to verify
that it is working.
And we can do that with sudo mount -a.
This command will try to mount
all the entries in the fstab file.
Hit enter, and we can see
that we have an error.
It says that the mount
point /mp does not exist.
I did this on purpose to show you that
the mount point has to be
given as the full path.
So if we come back over
here, you see that?
This is what we need to specify.
So let's do that.
I'm gonna hit the up arrow, sudo v1 fstab.
Insert, and I'm gonna go down
over here, make that change.
It's /home/ec2-user/mp.
Looks good.
Escape, :wq!, hit enter.
Let's do a cat fstab,
and this is the new entry that we made.
And finally, we can verify
that with sudo mount -a.
If you don't see any error message,
that means everything is good.
At this point the volume has
been mounted successfully,
and even if we reboot it is
gonna get mounted automatically.
It's not as easy as doing
on a Windows device.
It has a few steps.
But I hope you found that interesting.
I'd like to thank you for watching,
and I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.