- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video, we're gonna look at
the concepts of EBS snapshots.
Let's begin.
Alright, so what do we
mean by EBS snapshots?
Amazon EBS, also known
as Elastic Block Store,
provides the ability to create snapshots,
or in other words, backups,
of any EBS volume
and write a copy of the data
in the volume to Amazon S3
where it is stored redundantly
in multiple Availability Zones.
These snapshots can be used
to create multiple new EBS volumes
or to move volumes across
Availability Zones.
The snapshots can be shared
with specific AWS accounts
or even made public.
When you create snapshots,
you incur charges in Amazon S3
based on the volume's total size.
Snapshots are incremental backups,
which means only the blocks on the device
that have changed after your
most recent snapshot are saved.
This minimizes the time
required to create the snapshot
and saves on storage cost
by not duplicating data.
When you delete a snapshot,
only the data unique to
that snapshot is removed.
Each snapshot contains
all of the information
needed to restore your data
from the moment when
the snapshot was taken
to a new EBS volume.
When you create an EBS
volume based on a snapshot,
the new volume begins as an exact replica
of the original volume that was
used to create the snapshot.
The replicated volume loads
data lazily in the background
so that you can begin
using it immediately.
However, if you access data
that hasn't been loaded yet,
the volume immediately downloads
the requested data from Amazon S3,
and then continues loading the rest
of the volume's data in the background.
Alright, I have a diagram on the screen
that shows you how snapshots
actually store the data.
We have a volume which
is known as volume one,
and we are representing
three states of the volume,
state one, state two, and state three.
In state one, volume
one has 10 gigs of data.
At that point, we take a snapshot,
and that is called as snap A.
Snap A will have 10 gigs of data,
because this is the initial snapshot.
After snap A was taken,
we change four gigs of data on volume one.
After changing four gigs of data,
we take another snapshot called snap B.
In this case, snap B will
contain four gigs of data,
and for the remaining six gigs of data,
it will reference snap A.
After taking snap B,
we then added two gigs of data.
So at this point volume
one has 12 gigs of data,
and now we take a new
snapshot called snap C.
In this case, snap C would
have two gigs of data.
For the four gigs of data,
it would reference snap B,
and for the six gigs of data,
it would reference snap A.
As you can see, this method
helps you save on storage cost,
because otherwise snap A would be 10 gigs,
snap B would be 10 gigs,
and snap C would be 12 gigs,
a total of 32 gigs.
However, in this case, snap A is 10 gigs,
snap B is four gigs,
and snap C is two gigs,
which is 16 gigs of data,
which is half of the original one.
Moving on, let's talk about
copying and sharing snapshots.
Snapshots can be copied across regions,
making it possible to use multiple regions
for geographical expansion,
data center migration,
and disaster recovery.
Unencrypted snapshots can
be shared with co-workers,
AWS Community users or even made public.
You can make copies of your own snapshots
as well as snapshots that
have been shared with you.
However, encrypted
snapshots can only be shared
with specific AWS accounts and
you cannot make them public.
For other users to be able to
use the encrypted snapshot,
you must also share the
custom encryption key
used to encrypt the snapshot,
and we'll be seeing all of
this stuff in the next video.
Let's talk about encryption
support for snapshots.
Snapshots of encrypted volumes
are automatically encrypted.
In the last video, we saw
that volumes can be encrypted
at the time of creating them.
You can encrypt them when
you're adding a new volume
to the EC2 instance at the
time of launching the instance,
or otherwise when you're
creating a new volume
from the Volumes tab.
So, snapshots of encrypted volumes
are automatically encrypted
and volumes that are created
from encrypted snapshots
are also automatically encrypted.
When you copy an unencrypted
snapshot that you own,
you have the option to encrypt
it during the copy process.
When you copy an encrypted
snapshot that you own,
you can re-encrypt it with a different key
during the copy process.
Don't freak out if it
sounds too confusing.
I know it does.
In the next video,
I am going to show you all
of this live in action.
Right now, we're just
looking at the concepts.
Creating snapshots.
Snapshots occur asynchronously.
The point-in-time snapshot
is created immediately,
but the status of the snapshot is pending
until the snapshot is complete,
and this happens when all
of the modified blocks
have been transferred to Amazon S3.
This can take several hours
for large initial snapshots
or subsequent snapshots where
many blocks have changed.
While this is being completed,
an in-progress snapshot is not affected
by ongoing reads and writes to the volume.
We can take a snapshot
of an attached volume
that is in use, and this is fantastic
because we don't have to remove the volume
from the EC2 instance
before taking the snapshot.
We can do it while it is being used.
However, snapshots only capture data
that have been written
to your Amazon EBS volume
at the time the snapshot
command was issued.
However, if there's any data
that is sitting in the cache,
that will not be found on the snapshot.
For complete snapshots,
file writes to volumes should be paused.
However, if you cannot pause
all file writes to the volume,
you should unmount the volume
from within the instance,
issue the snapshot command,
and then remount the volume
to ensure a consistent
and complete snapshot.
Very important.
To create a snapshot for an EBS volume
that serves as a root device,
you should stop the instance
before taking the snapshot.
Well, that's it for this video.
In the next video we'll be implementing
all of these concepts on the AWS Console.
I'm excited to see you there,
and I'd like to thank you for watching.
Thank you.