- [Instructor] Welcome back.
In this video, we're gonna look at
EBS snapshots live in action.
All the concepts that we
discussed in the last video,
we're gonna implement
all of these concepts.
All right, so I'm logged
into the AWS console
and right now I'm in the EC2 section
and I'm gonna first click on Volumes.
As you can see, right now
I do not have any volumes.
So I'm gonna first create a new volume.
So I'm gonna say, Create Volume.
And we can choose any one
of these types over here.
I'm gonna go for a General Purpose SSD.
And I'm gonna give the size as 1 gig.
And I'm gonna choose the
Availability Zone as us-east-1a.
We can choose to encrypt the volume,
but right now, I'm just
gonna say Create Volume.
So, the volume has now been created.
We can see that over here.
And, the State of available means that
it has not been associated or
attached with an EC2 instance.
Let's try to create a
snapshot for this volume.
So I'll go to Actions over here
and I'm gonna say Create Snapshot.
At this point, we can give it a name.
Let's call it as Snap-1.
Notice that it says Encrypted No.
Since the original
volume was not encrypted,
I do not have the option
to encrypt the snapshot.
I'm gonna say, Create, and
the snapshot creation has started.
We can click over here
or we can close this
and go to Shapshots over here.
And the snapshot has been created.
Now, if we wanted to restore
the snapshot into a volume,
we could go to Actions, and
we can say Create Volume.
Let's try that.
Notice that, when you're
restoring back to a volume,
you have the option to change the type,
which is interesting.
We also have the option
to change the size.
And, most important,
we also have the option
to change the Availability
Zone, which means,
if we want to move a volume
across Availability Zones,
we first need to create
a snapshot and then
restore the snapshot into
the new Availability Zone.
For example, I'm gonna say, us-east-1b
and I'm gonna click on Create Volume.
I'm gonna close this and go
back to Volumes over here.
And we can see that now
we have two volumes.
This is the original one,
which was us-east-1a.
And this is the restored
volume, us-east-1b.
Let's try this one more time.
But this time, we're gonna
go for an encrypted volume.
So Create Volume.
GP2, General Purpose SSD.
Size is 1 gig.
And the Availability Zone is us-east-1a.
But this time I'm gonna
say Encrypt this volume.
You have the option to
select the default key.
Or, if you have a custom key,
you could choose that as well.
In fact, let me take you to Mumbai
where I believe I have a
new key present over there.
So I'm gonna take you back over here.
Notice the region has
now changed to Mumbai.
And I'm gonna change the size to 1 gig.
And I'm gonna say Encryption, turned on.
Over here you'll notice that I
have two keys to choose from.
This is the default key and
this is the key that I created.
So you could use your
own custom keys as well.
I'm gonna go back over here
and I'm gonna perform the lab from here.
I'm gonna use the default key.
And I'm gonna say, Create
Volume, click on Close,
and now we can see the
volume has been created.
So I'm just gonna go down and
verify that this is the one.
Yup, encrypted.
And let's give it a name
for identification purpose.
Let's call it as Encrypted Volume.
Now I'm gonna create a
snapshot out of this.
So Actions, Create Snapshot.
Notice what happens over here.
It automatically turns on encryption
and we do not have the option
to turn off encryption.
Let's give it a name.
Let's call it as Encrypted Snap.
Click on Create.
And click on Close and go
back to Snapshots over here.
So this is the snapshot that
is being created right now.
The snapshot creation has completed.
Let's try to create a volume out of it.
So Actions, Create Volume.
I want you to notice this guys.
There is no way to turn that off.
The volume will also be encrypted.
This is very, very important
for us to understand,
that once your original
volume has been encrypted,
the snapshot will be encrypted
and the volume that is
created out of that snapshot
will also be encrypted.
You don't have the option to turn it off.
Let's cancel out of here.
And let me show you
how to copy a snapshot.
So you can select your snapshot.
You can go to Actions,
and we can say Copy.
When you select Copy, you have
the option to change the region.
So, for example, if I
wanted to move this over to,
let's say, Mumbai, I can select that.
I can give it a nice description
and here, I have the
option to change the key.
So when you're moving across the region,
you have the option to select your key.
And this key is what I
have in the Mumbai region.
So I can select my key over here.
Well let me do this, let
me select the other one.
We can say Copy.
So now, it is being moved
over to the Mumbai region.
So I'm gonna close this and
go back to Mumbai over here.
Cancel out of here, go to Snapshots
and you can see that the snapshot
creation has now started.
So, in this way, we can create
snapshots out of volumes
and we can move them across.
In the last video, we understood that
snapshots are actually
stored in Amazon S3.
However, if you visited the AWS S3 console
you would not find your
snapshots over there.
In fact, we can take a look at it.
I'll go to Services, and I'll open up S3
in a new tab over here.
And you can see over here,
I do not have any bucket where
my snapshots are created.
In fact, these are all my
existing and old buckets.
There's no new bucket that
contains the snapshots.
So, even though snapshots
are stored in Amazon S3,
you don't see them from the S3 console.
You can only see them
from the AWS EC2 console.
And, by the way, I just
noticed that it says, error.
I have no idea why that has happened.
Let's do a refresh.
Now it says pending.
So probably it should now complete.
So that's about EBS snapshots.
I'd like to thank you for watching.
And I'll catch you in the next video.
Thank you.